<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>

<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<rfc
 docName="draft-ietf-nfsv4-rpcrdma-version-two-latest"
 category="std"
 ipr="pre5378Trust200902">

<front>

<title abbrev="RPC-over-RDMA Version 2">
RPC-over-RDMA Version 2 Protocol
</title>

<author initials="C.L." surname="Lever" fullname="Charles Lever" role="editor">
<organization abbrev="Oracle">Oracle Corporation</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city></city>
<region></region>
<code></code>
<country>United States of America</country>
</postal>
<email>chuck.lever@oracle.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<author initials="D.N." surname="Noveck" fullname="David Noveck">
<organization>NetApp</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>1601 Trapelo Road</street>
<city>Waltham</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02451</code>
<country>United States of America</country>
</postal>
<phone>+1 781 572 8038</phone>
<email>davenoveck@gmail.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<date />

<area>Transport</area>
<workgroup>Network File System Version 4</workgroup>
<keyword>NFS-Over-RDMA</keyword>

<abstract>
<t>
This document specifies the second version
of a transport protocol that conveys
Remote Procedure Call (RPC) messages
using Remote Direct Memory Access (RDMA).
This version of the protocol is extensible.
</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section
 anchor="section:72f6ba4a-aafb-4e9d-8b87-800ebccc5879"
 title="Introduction">
<t>
Remote Direct Memory Access (RDMA)
<xref target="RFC5040"/>
<xref target="RFC5041"/>
<xref target="IBA"/>
is a technique for moving data efficiently between network nodes.
By placing transferred data directly into destination buffers
using Direct Memory Access, RDMA delivers the reciprocal benefits of
faster data transfer
and
reduced host CPU overhead.
</t>
<t>
Open Network Computing Remote Procedure Call
(ONC RPC, often shortened in NFSv4 documents to RPC)
<xref target="RFC5531"/>
is a Remote Procedure Call protocol
that runs over a variety of transports.
Most RPC implementations today use
UDP
<xref target="RFC0768"/>
or
TCP
<xref target="RFC0793"/>.
On UDP, a datagram encapsulates each RPC message.
Within a TCP byte stream,
a record marking protocol delineates RPC messages.
</t>
<t>
An RDMA transport, too, conveys RPC messages
in a fashion that must be fully defined
if RPC implementations are to interoperate
when using RDMA to transport RPC transactions.
Although RDMA transports encapsulate messages like UDP,
they deliver them reliably and in order, like TCP.
Further, they implement a bulk data transfer service
not provided by traditional network transports.
Therefore, we treat RDMA as a novel transport type for RPC.
</t>
<t>
The RPC-over-RDMA transport introduced in the current document
can transparently support any RPC application.
The current document describes mechanisms that
enable further optimization of data transfer
when RPC applications are structured
to exploit direct data placement.
In this context, the Network File System (NFS) protocols,
as described in
<xref target="RFC1094"/>,
<xref target="RFC1813"/>,
<xref target="RFC7530"/>,
<xref target="RFC5661"/>,
and subsequent NFSv4 minor versions,
are all potential beneficiaries of RPC-over-RDMA.
A complete problem statement appears in
<xref target="RFC5532"/>.
</t>
<t>
Storage administrators have broadly deployed
the RPC-over-RDMA version 1 protocol specified in
<xref target="RFC8166"/>.
However, there are known shortcomings to this protocol:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The protocol's default size of Receive buffers forces
the use of RDMA Read and Write transfers for small payloads,
and limits the size of reverse direction messages.
</t>
<t>
It is difficult to make optimizations or protocol fixes
that require changes to on-the-wire behavior.
</t>
<t>
For some RPC procedures, the maximum reply size is
difficult or impossible for an RPC client to estimate
in advance.
</t>
</list>
To address these issues in a way that preserves interoperation
with existing RPC-over-RDMA version 1 deployments,
we present a second version of the RPC-over-RDMA transport protocol
in the current document.
</t>
<t>
The version of RPC-over-RDMA presented here is extensible,
enabling the introduction of OPTIONAL extensions
without impacting existing implementations.
See
<xref target="section:d945b9f0-0666-4db7-9126-be57cf7b5f4f"/>,
for further discussion.
It introduces a mechanism to exchange implementation properties
to automatically provide further optimization of data transfer.
</t>
<t>
This version also contains incremental changes that
relieve performance constraints
and
enable recovery from unusual corner cases.
These changes are outlined in
<xref target="section:c2574344-5aec-427d-a5ed-048d7fcc0d95"/>
and include
a larger default inline threshold,
the ability to convey a single RPC message using multiple RDMA Send operations,
support for authentication of connection peers,
richer error reporting,
improved credit-based flow control,
and
support for Remote Invalidation.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:ef1a2819-4d22-40af-8d38-fde10849c872"
 title="Requirements Language">
<t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted
as described in BCP 14
<xref target="RFC2119"/>
<xref target="RFC8174"/>
when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:4dc39c9c-3770-491f-b674-f824e87e2143"
 title="Terminology">

<section
 anchor="section:4d675e45-c377-48df-8029-c5c9f8c48f9f"
 title="Remote Procedure Calls">
<t>
This section highlights critical elements of the RPC protocol
<xref target="RFC5531"/>
and
the External Data Representation (XDR)
<xref target="RFC4506"/>
it uses.
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 enables
the transmission of RPC messges built using XDR
and
also uses XDR internally to describe its header formats.
The remainder of this document requires
an understanding of RPC and its use of XDR.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:8d804fe5-c7c7-4c6c-92d8-888da10caaec"
 title="Upper-Layer Protocols">
<t>
RPCs are an abstraction used to implement the operations of an Upper-Layer Protocol (ULP).
For RPC-over-RDMA, "ULP" refers to an RPC Program and Version tuple,
which is a versioned set of procedure calls that comprise a single well-defined API.
One example of a ULP is the Network File System Version 4.0
<xref target="RFC7530"/>.
In the current document, the term "RPC consumer" refers to
an implementation of a ULP running on an RPC client.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:17a77782-8b11-4fb5-af0b-e0da7759c10A"
 title="Requesters and Responders">
<t>
Like a local procedure call,
every RPC procedure has a set of "arguments" and a set of "results".
A calling context invokes a procedure,
passing arguments to it,
and the procedure subsequently returns a set of results.
Unlike a local procedure call,
the called procedure is executed remotely rather than
in the local application's execution context.
</t>
<t>
The RPC protocol as described in
<xref target="RFC5531"/>
is fundamentally a message-passing protocol
between one or more clients, where RPC consumers are running,
and a server, where a remote execution context is available
to process RPC transactions on behalf of these consumers.
</t>
<t>
ONC RPC transactions consist of two types of messages:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
A CALL message, or "Call", requests work.
An RPC Call message is designated
by the value zero (0) in the message's msg_type field.
The sender places a unique 32-bit value in the message's XID field
to match this RPC Call message to a corresponding RPC Reply message.
</t>
<t>
A REPLY message, or "Reply",
reports the results of work requested by an RPC Call message.
An RPC Reply message is designated
by the value one (1) in the message's msg_type field.
The sender copies the value contained in an RPC Reply message's XID field
from the RPC Call message whose results the sender is reporting.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Each RPC client endpoint acts as a "Requester",
which serializes the procedure's arguments
and
conveys them to a server endpoint via an RPC Call message.
A Call message contains an RPC protocol header,
a header describing the requested upper-layer operation,
and all arguments.
</t>
<t>
An RPC server endpoint acts as a "Responder",
which deserializes the arguments and processes the requested operation.
It then serializes the operation's results into an RPC Reply message.
An RPC Reply message contains an RPC protocol header,
a header describing the upper-layer reply,
and all results.
</t>
<t>
The Requester deserializes the results
and
allows the RPC consumer to proceed.
At this point, the RPC transaction
designated by the XID in the RPC Call message is complete,
and the XID is retired.
</t>
<t>
In summary,
Requesters send RPC Call messages to Responders
to initiate RPC transactions.
Responders send RPC Reply messages to Requesters
to complete the processing on an RPC transaction.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:63f47fcd-629b-4b00-aa8b-dbf836401581"
 title="RPC Transports">
<t>
The role of an "RPC transport" is
to mediate the exchange of RPC messages
between Requesters and Responders.
An RPC transport bridges the gap
between the RPC message abstraction
and
the native operations of a network transport
(e.g., a socket).
</t>
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA is a connection-oriented RPC transport.
When a transport type is connection-oriented,
clients initiate transport connections,
while servers wait passively to accept incoming connection requests.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:2432566f-67e7-4f35-8ec4-9ed44cecd8cc"
 title="Forward Direction">
<t>
Traditionally, an RPC client acts as a Requester,
while an RPC service acts as a Responder.
The current document
refers to this form of RPC message passing
as "forward-direction" operation.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:189a59d0-9235-4c1e-a76f-ea2b20fd6c94"
 title="Reverse-Direction">
<t>
The RPC specification
<xref target="RFC5531"/>
does not forbid passing RPC messages
in the other direction.
An RPC service endpoint can act as a Requester,
in which case an RPC client endpoint acts as a Responder.
This form of message passing is known as
"reverse-direction" operation.
</t>
<t>
During reverse-direction operation,
an RPC client is responsible
for establishing transport connections,
even though the RPC server originates RPC Calls.
</t>
<t>
RPC clients and servers are usually optimized
to perform and scale well when handling traffic
in the forward direction.
They might not be prepared to handle operation
in the reverse direction.
Not until NFS version 4.1
<xref target="RFC5661"/>
has there been a strong need
to handle reverse-direction operation.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:05f24e3b-ad49-4370-a0fe-477b0f1364aa"
 title="Bi-directional Operation">
<t>
A pair of connected RPC endpoints may choose to use
only forward-direction
or
only reverse-direction operation
on a particular transport connection.
Or, these endpoints may send Calls
in both directions concurrently
on the same transport connection.
</t>
<t>
"Bi-directional operation" occurs when both transport endpoints
act as a Requester and a Responder at the same time
on a single connection.
</t>
<t>
Bi-directionality is an extension
of RPC transport connection sharing.
Two RPC endpoints wish to exchange
independent RPC messages over a shared connection
but in opposite directions.
These messages may or may not be related
to the same workloads or RPC Programs.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:97382254-b1a3-4e03-98e5-a0814b331bd0"
 title="XID Values">
<t>
Section 9 of
<xref target="RFC5531"/>
introduces the RPC transaction identifier,
or "XID" for short.
A connection peer interprets the value of an XID
in the context of the message's msg_type field.
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The XID of a Call is arbitrary but is
unique among outstanding Calls from that Requester
on that connection.
</t>
<t>
The XID of a Reply always matches
that of the initiating Call.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
After receiving a Reply,
a Requester matches the XID value in that Reply
with a Call it previously sent.
</t>
<t>
During bi-directional operation,
forward- and reverse- direction XIDs
are typically generated
on distinct hosts by possibly different algorithms.
There is no coordination between the generation of XIDs
used in forward-direction and reverse-direction operation.
</t>
<t>
Therefore, a forward-direction Requester
MAY use the same XID value at the same time
as a reverse-direction Requester
on the same transport connection.
Although such concurrent requests use the same XID value,
they represent distinct RPC transactions.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:98bdc62c-0af4-4379-8b5c-6d98b7a520c7"
 title="External Data Representation">
<t>
One cannot assume that all Requesters and Responders
represent data objects in the same way internally.
RPC uses External Data Representation (XDR)
to translate native data types and serialize arguments and results
<xref target="RFC4506"/>.
</t>
<t>
XDR encodes data independently
of the endianness or size of host-native data types,
enabling unambiguous decoding of data by a receiver.
</t>
<t>
XDR assumes only that the number of bits in a byte (octet)
and
their order are the same on both endpoints and the physical network.
The smallest indivisible unit of XDR encoding is a group of four octets.
XDR can also flatten
lists,
arrays,
and
other complex data types
into a stream of bytes.
</t>
<t>
We refer to a serialized stream of bytes
that is the result of XDR encoding
as an "XDR stream".
A sender encodes native data
into an XDR stream and then transmits that stream to a receiver.
The receiver decodes incoming XDR byte streams
into its native data representation format.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:c6d3092c-99e6-4cce-b377-fffc4862929F"
 title="XDR Opaque Data">
<t>
Sometimes, a data item is to be transferred as-is,
without encoding or decoding.
We refer to the contents of such a data item as "opaque data".
XDR encoding places the content of opaque data items
directly into an XDR stream without altering it in any way.
ULPs or applications perform
any needed data translation in this case.
Examples of opaque data items include the content of files
or generic byte strings.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:c210323f-c524-4e98-a02d-23549a4bebc5"
 title="XDR Roundup">
<t>
The number of octets in a variable-length data item
precedes that item in an XDR stream.
If the size of an encoded data item is not a multiple of four octets,
the sender appends octets containing zero after the end of the data item.
These zero octets shift the next encoded data item in the XDR stream
so that it always starts on a four-octet boundary.
The addition of extra octets does not change
the encoded size of the data item.
Receivers do not expose the extra octets to ULPs.
</t>
<t>
We refer to this technique as "XDR roundup",
and the extra octets as "XDR roundup padding".
</t>
</section>

</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:de830270-64ed-4510-ac25-29837d352031"
 title="Remote Direct Memory Access">
<t>
When a third party transfers large RPC payloads,
RPC Requesters and Responders can become more efficient.
An example of such a third party might be
an intelligent network interface
(data movement offload),
which places data in the receiver's memory so that
no additional adjustment of data alignment is necessary
(direct data placement or "DDP").
RDMA transports enable both of these optimizations.
</t>
<t>
In the current document, "RDMA" refers to
the physical mechanism an RDMA transport utilizes when moving data.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:1b97ecfd-7aba-4299-9007-dab28ac76f81"
 title="Direct Data Placement">
<t>
Typically, RPC implementations copy
the contents of RPC messages into a buffer before being sent.
An efficient RPC implementation sends bulk data
without copying it into a separate send buffer first.
</t>
<t>
However, socket-based RPC implementations
are often unable to receive data directly
into its final place in memory.
Receivers often need to copy incoming data
to finish an RPC operation
sometimes, if only to adjust data alignment.
</t>
<t>
Although it may not be efficient,
before an RDMA transfer, a sender may copy data into an intermediate buffer.
After an RDMA transfer, a receiver may copy that data again to its final destination.
In this document, the term "DDP" refers to
any optimized data transfer where a receiving host's CPU
does not move transferred data
to another location after arrival.
</t>
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 enables the use of RDMA Read and Write operations
to achieve both data movement offload and DDP.
However, note that
not all RDMA-based data transfer qualifies as DDP,
and
some mechanisms that do not employ explicit RDMA can place data directly.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:6903045e-bd1c-4e12-bf96-6b534989f46A"
 title="RDMA Transport Requirements">
<t>
RDMA transports require that
RDMA consumers provision resources in advance
to achieve good performance during receive operations.
An RDMA consumer might provide Receive buffers in advance
by posting an RDMA Receive Work Request
for every expected RDMA Send from a remote peer.
These buffers are provided
before the remote peer posts RDMA Send Work Requests.
Thus this is often referred to as "pre-posting" buffers.
</t>
<t>
An RDMA Receive Work Request remains outstanding
until the RDMA provider matches it to an inbound Send operation.
The resources associated with that Receive must be retained in
host memory, or "pinned", until the Receive completes.
</t>
<t>
Given these tenets of operation,
the RPC-over-RDMA version 2 protocol assumes
each transport provides the following abstract operations.
A more complete discussion of these operations appears in
<xref target="RFC5040"/>.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:90f88ba5-5ad6-4ac1-b40d-ed9247e61ca5"
 title="Memory Registration">
<t>
Memory registration assigns a steering tag
to a region of memory,
permitting the RDMA provider
to perform data-transfer operations.
The RPC-over-RDMA version 2 protocol assumes that
a steering tag of no more than 32 bits and memory
addresses of up to 64 bits in length
identifies each registered memory region.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:07bba55f-c48f-474c-918b-db6c9d2325dd"
 title="RDMA Send">
<t>
The RDMA provider supports an RDMA Send operation,
with completion signaled on the receiving peer
after RDMA provider has placed data in a pre-posted buffer.
Sends complete at the receiver
in the order they were posted at the sender.
The size of the remote peer's pre-posted buffers
limits the amount of data
that can be transferred by a single RDMA Send operation.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:9be6a44c-1ea5-4ccd-b188-ee04e930497b"
 title="RDMA Receive">
<t>
The RDMA provider supports an RDMA Receive operation
to receive data conveyed by incoming RDMA Send operations.
To reduce the amount of memory that must remain pinned
awaiting incoming Sends,
the amount of memory posted per Receive is limited.
The RDMA consumer (in this case, the RPC-over-RDMA version 2 protocol)
provides flow control to prevent overrunning receiver resources.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:cfd79bce-e8e9-4a51-b43a-b747af6213f4"
 title="RDMA Write">
<t>
The RDMA provider supports an RDMA Write operation
to place data directly into a remote memory region.
The local host initiates an RDMA Write
and the RDMA provider signals completion there.
The remote RDMA provider does not signal completion
on the remote peer.
The local host provides
the steering tag,
the memory address,
and
the length of the remote peer's memory region.
</t>
<t>
RDMA Writes are not ordered relative to one another,
but are ordered relative to RDMA Sends.
Thus, a subsequent RDMA Send completion
signaled on the local peer
guarantees that prior RDMA Write data
has been successfully placed in the remote peer's memory.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:f37121af-49ff-4575-a699-7310f4ae1296"
 title="RDMA Read">
<t>
The RDMA provider supports an RDMA Read operation
to place remote source data directly into local memory.
The local host initiates an RDMA Read
and and the RDMA provider signals completion there.
The remote RDMA provider does not signal
completion on the remote peer.
The local host provides
the steering tags,
the memory addresses,
and the lengths for the remote source
and
local destination memory regions.
</t>
<t>
The RDMA consumer (in this case, the RPC-over-RDMA version 2 protocol)
signals Read completion to the remote peer
as part of a subsequent RDMA Send message.
The remote peer can then invalidate steering tags
and
subsequently free associated source memory regions.
</t>
</section>

</section>

</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:5ae4b016-9b44-4649-9021-5ae851ac9326"
 title="RPC-over-RDMA Framework">
<t>
Before an RDMA data transfer can occur,
an endpoint first exposes regions of its memory to a remote endpoint.
The remote endpoint then initiates RDMA Read and Write operations
against the exposed memory.
A "transfer model" designates
which endpoint exposes its memory
and
which is responsible for initiating the transfer of data.
</t>
<t>
In RPC-over-RDMA version 2,
only Requesters expose their memory to the Responder,
and only Responders initiate RDMA Read and Write operations.
Read access to memory regions enables the Responder to
pull RPC arguments
or
whole RPC Calls from each Requester.
The Responder pushes
RPC results
or
whole RPC Replies to a Requester's
memory regions to which it has write access.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:195e0288-862d-40bb-a259-4239930c728a"
 title="Message Framing">
<t>
Each RPC-over-RDMA version 2 message consists of at most two XDR streams:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The "Transport stream" contains a header that describes
and controls the transfer of the Payload stream
in this RPC-over-RDMA message.
Every RDMA Send on an RPC-over-RDMA version 2 connection
MUST begin with a Transport stream.
</t>
<t>
The "Payload stream" contains part or all of a single RPC message.
The sender MAY divide an RPC message at any convenient boundary
but
MUST send RPC message fragments in XDR stream order
and
MUST NOT interleave Payload streams from multiple RPC messages.
The RPC-over-RDMA version 2 message carrying the final part
of an RPC message is marked (see
<xref target="section:fb299673-74f3-4f01-adb5-26a02ccd679f"/>).
</t>
</list>
The RPC-over-RDMA framing mechanism described in this section
replaces all other RPC framing mechanisms.
Connection peers use RPC-over-RDMA framing
even when the underlying RDMA protocol runs
on a transport type with well-defined RPC framing, such as TCP.
However, a ULP can negotiate the use of RDMA,
dynamically enabling the use of RPC-over-RDMA on a connection
established on some other transport type.
Because RPC framing delimits an entire RPC request or reply,
the resulting shift in framing must occur between distinct RPC messages,
and in concert with the underlying transport.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:130ce79c-8b13-479e-8108-a943024047dD"
 title="Managing Receiver Resources">
<t>
If any pre-posted Receive buffer on the connection
is not large enough to accept an incoming RDMA Send,
the RDMA provider can terminate the connection.
Likewise, if a pre-posted Receive buffer is not available
to accept an incoming RDMA Send,
the RDMA provider can terminate the connection.
Therefore, a sender needs to respect the resource limits of its peer receiver
to ensure the longevity of each connection.
Two operational parameters communicate these limits between connection peers:
flow control, and inline threshold.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:45c67eb8-8dc6-47c3-8555-14270f1514bF"
 title="Flow Control">
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA requires reliable and in-order delivery of data payloads.
Therefore, RPC-over-RDMA transports MUST use
the RDMA RC (Reliable Connected) Queue Pair (QP) type.
The use of an RC QP ensures
in-transit data integrity
and
proper recovery from packet loss or misordering.
</t>
<t>
However, RPC-over-RDMA itself provides a flow control mechanism
to prevent a sender from overwhelming receiver resources.
RPC-over-RDMA transports employ
end-to-end credit-based flow control for this purpose
<xref target="CBFC"/>.
Credit-based flow control is relatively simple, providing
robust operation in the face of bursty traffic
and
automated management of receive buffer allocation.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:278fca6a-f2a8-42f3-a4e9-a8d4b217567e"
 title="Granting Credits">
<t>
An RPC-over-RDMA version 2 credit is
the capability to receive one RPC-over-RDMA version 2 message.
This arrangement enables RPC-over-RDMA version 2 to
support asymmetrical operation,
where a message in one direction might trigger zero, one, or multiple
messages in the other direction in response.
</t>
<t>
To achieve this,
each posted Receive buffer on both connection peers receives one credit.
Each Requester has a set of Receive credits,
and
each Responder has a set of Receive credits.
These credit values are managed independently of one another.
</t>
<t>
Section 7 of
<xref target="RFC8166"/>
requires that the 32-bit field containing the credit grant is the
third word in the transport header.
To conform with that requirement,
senders encode the two independent credit values into a single
32-bit field in the fixed portion of the transport header.
At the receiver, the low-order two bytes are the number of credits
that are newly granted by the sender.
The granted credit value MUST NOT be zero
since such a value would result in deadlock.
The high-order two bytes are the maximum number of credits that
can be outstanding at the sender.
</t>
<t>
A sender must avoid posting more RDMA Send messages than
the receiver's granted credit limit.
If the sender exceeds the granted value,
the RDMA provider might signal an error,
possibly terminating the connection.
</t>
<t>
The granted credit values MAY be adjusted
to match the needs or policies in effect on either peer.
For instance, a peer may reduce its granted credit
value to accommodate the available resources in a Shared Receive Queue.
</t>
<t>
Certain RDMA implementations may impose additional flow-control restrictions,
such as limits on RDMA Read operations in progress at the Responder.
Accommodation of such restrictions is considered
the responsibility of each RPC-over-RDMA version 2 implementation.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:f6348562-97f8-4413-96d7-bde3ff57b375"
 title="Asynchronous Credit Grants">
<t>
A special protocol convention enables one peer
to refresh its credit grant to the other peer
without sending a payload.
Messages of this type can also act as a keep-alive ping.
See
<xref target="section:1c401555-4b7d-4e35-a9a3-8aa14228170e"/>
for information about this convention.
</t>
<t>
Receivers MUST always be in a position to receive
one such credit grant update message,
in addition to payload-bearing messages,
to prevent transport deadlock.
One way a receiver can do this is to post one more RDMA Receive
than the credit value the receiver granted.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:653e7ab4-782f-43f2-947f-d097ada8b3c9"
 title="Inline Threshold">
<t>
An "inline threshold" value is the largest message size
(in octets) that can be conveyed in one direction between
peer implementations using RDMA Send and Receive channel operations.
An inline threshold value is less than the largest number of octets
the sender can post in a single RDMA Send operation.
It is also less than the largest number of octets
the receiver can reliably accept via a single RDMA Receive operation.
</t>
<t>
Each connection has two inline threshold values.
There is one for messages flowing from Requester-to-Responder,
referred to as the "call inline threshold",
and one for messages flowing from Responder-to-Requester,
referred to as the "reply inline threshold."
</t>
<t>
Peers can advertise their inline threshold values
via RPC-over-RDMA version 2 Transport Properties (see
<xref target="section:86248e99-ca60-478a-8aff-3fb387410077"/>).
In the absence of an exchange of Transport Properties,
connection peers MUST assume both inline thresholds are 4096 octets.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:9563f1f0-28a7-48e1-a752-e842575c6539"
 title="Initial Connection State">
<t>
When an RPC-over-RDMA version 2 client establishes
a connection to a server,
its first order of business is
to determine the server's highest supported protocol version.
</t>
<t>
Upon connection establishment, a client MUST send
only a single RPC-over-RDMA message until
it receives a valid RPC-over-RDMA message
from the server that grants client credits.
</t>
<t>
The second word of each transport header conveys
the transport protocol version.
In the interest of clarity,
the current document refers to that word as rdma_vers
even though in the RPC-over-RDMA version 2 XDR definition,
it appears as rdma_start.rdma_vers.
</t>
<t>
Immediately after the client establishes a connection,
it sends a single valid RPC-over-RDMA message
with the value two (2) in the rdma_vers field.
Because the server might support
only RPC-over-RDMA version 1,
this initial message MUST NOT be larger than
the version 1 default inline threshold of 1024 octets.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:8db4c54e-c1ce-43ba-93b4-031e829960f5"
 title="Server Does Support RPC-over-RDMA Version 2">
<t>
If the server supports RPC-over-RDMA version 2,
it sends RPC-over-RDMA messages back to the client
with the value two (2) in the rdma_vers field.
Both peers may assume the default inline threshold value
for RPC-over-RDMA version 2 connections (4096 octets).
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:bedc4e66-4295-4dd6-8ac9-dd06907a08ad"
 title="Server Does Not Support RPC-over-RDMA Version 2">
<t>
If the server does not support RPC-over-RDMA version 2,
it MUST send an RPC-over-RDMA message to the client
with an XID that matches the client's first message,
RDMA2_ERROR in the rdma_start.rdma_htype field,
and with the error code RDMA2_ERR_VERS.
This message also reports the range
of RPC-over-RDMA protocol versions that the server supports.
To continue operation, the client selects
a protocol version in that range
for subsequent messages on this connection.
</t>
<t>
If the connection is dropped immediately after an
RDMA2_ERROR/RDMA2_ERR_VERS message is received,
the client should try to avoid a version negotiation loop
when re-establishing another connection.
It can assume that the server
does not support RPC-over-RDMA version 2.
A client can assume the same situation
(i.e., no server support for RPC-over-RDMA version 2)
if the initial negotiation message is lost or dropped.
Once the version negotiation exchange is complete,
both peers may use the default inline threshold value
for the negotiated transport protocol version.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:1ffe4c69-b516-476a-bba7-41863709f48d"
 title="Client Does Not Support RPC-over-RDMA Version 2">
<t>
The server examines the RPC-over-RDMA protocol version
used in the first RPC-over-RDMA message it receives.
If it supports this protocol version,
it MUST use it in all subsequent messages it sends on that connection.
The client MUST NOT change the protocol version
for the duration of the connection.
</t>
</section>

</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:cfa8877c-b905-455d-b420-bf7a4a7f7829"
 title="XDR Encoding with Chunks">
<t>
When a DDP capability is available,
an RDMA provider can place the contents
of one or more XDR data items
directly into a receiver's memory.
It can do this
separately from the transfer of other parts of the containing XDR stream.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:0e225040-d15f-4e9a-a0c3-afa115bb12c7"
 title="Reducing an XDR Stream">
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 provides a mechanism
for moving part of an RPC message via a data transfer
distinct from an RDMA Send/Receive pair.
The sender removes one or more XDR data items from the Payload stream.
These items are conveyed via other mechanisms,
such as one or more RDMA Read or Write operations.
As the receiver decodes an incoming message,
it skips over directly placed data items.
</t>
<t>
We refer to a data item that a sender removes from a Payload stream
to transmit separately as a "reduced" data item.
After a sender has finished removing XDR data items from a Payload stream,
we refer to it as a "reduced" Payload stream.
The data object in a transport header that
describes memory regions containing reduced data items
is known as a "chunk."
</t>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:155d7e5e-821b-485a-9b68-1248b7e35743"
 title="DDP-Eligibility">
<t>
Not all XDR data items benefit from Direct Data Placement.
For example, small data items
or
data items that require XDR unmarshaling by the receiver
do not benefit from DDP.
Moreover, it is impractical for receivers to prepare for every possible XDR data item in a protocol to appear in a chunk.
</t>
<t>
Determining which data items are DDP-eligible is done
in additional specifications that describe how ULPs employ DDP.
A "ULB specification" identifies which XDR data items
a peer MAY transfer using DDP.
Such data items are known as "DDP-eligible."
Senders MUST NOT reduce any other XDR data items.
Detailed requirements for ULB specifications appear in
<xref target="section:9e003b83-66b5-43d7-b9ef-0f271c8d301b"/>.
of the current document.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:8966c401-1714-413c-9384-b1f71f0a920d"
 title="RDMA Segments">
<t>
When encoding a Payload stream that contains a DDP-eligible data item,
a sender may choose to reduce that data item.
When it chooses to do so, the sender does not place the item
into the Payload stream.
Instead, the sender records in the transport header
the location and size of the memory region containing that data item.
</t>
<t>
The Requester provides location information for DDP-eligible data items
in both RPC Call and Reply messages.
The Responder uses this information
to retrieve arguments contained in the specified region of the Requester's memory
or
place results in that memory region.
</t>
<t>
An "RDMA segment", or "plain segment",
is a transport header data object
that contains the precise coordinates of a contiguous memory region.
This region is conveyed separately from the Payload stream.
Each RDMA segment contains the following information:
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Handle:">
A steering Tag (STag) or R_key generated by registering this memory with the RDMA provider.
</t>
<t hangText="Length:">
The length of the RDMA segment's memory region, in octets.
An "empty segment" is an RDMA segment
with the value zero (0) in its length field.
</t>
<t hangText="Offset:">
The offset or beginning memory address of the RDMA segment's memory region.
</t>
</list>
See
<xref target="RFC5040"/>
for further discussion.
 </t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:c561e45c-fe88-47e3-bdfd-689d482fcad3"
 title="Chunks">
<t>
In RPC-over-RDMA version 2,
a "chunk" refers to a portion of an RPC message
that is moved independently
of the Payload stream.
The sender removes chunk data from the Payload stream,
transfers it via separate operations,
and then the receiver reinserts it into the received Payload stream
to reconstruct the complete RPC message.
</t>
<t>
Each chunk consists of RDMA segments.
Each RDMA segment represents a piece of a chunk that is contiguous in memory.
A Requester MAY divide a chunk into RDMA segments
using any convenient boundaries.
The length of a chunk is precisely
the sum of the lengths of the RDMA segments that comprise it.
</t>
<t>
The RPC-over-RDMA version 2 transport protocol
does not place a limit on chunk size.
However, each ULP may cap the amount of data that can be transferred
by a single RPC transaction.
For example, NFS has "rsize" and "wsize", which restrict the payload size
of NFS READ and WRITE operations.
The Responder can use such limits to sanity check chunk sizes
before using them in RDMA operations.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:2b8d1299-b521-4198-b99c-25b4e344b8bb"
 title="Counted Arrays">
<t>
If a chunk is to contain a counted array data type,
the count of array elements MUST remain in the Payload stream.
The sender MUST move the array elements into the chunk.
For example, when encoding an opaque byte array as a chunk,
the count of bytes stays in the Payload stream.
The sender removes the bytes in the array from the Payload stream
and places them in the chunk.
</t>
<t>
Individual array elements appear in a chunk
in their entirety.
For example, when encoding an array of arrays as a chunk,
the count of items in the enclosing array stays in the Payload stream.
But each enclosed array, including its item count,
is transferred as part of the chunk.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:ec322087-6d38-42b9-b24b-831aabcfb5f9"
 title="Optional-Data">
<t>
If a chunk contains an optional-data data type,
the "is present" field MUST remain in the Payload stream.
The sender MUST move the data, if present, to the chunk.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:5ae887e6-fd9d-4a9f-a298-925b87a6a5b2"
 title="XDR Unions">
<t>
A union data type MUST NOT be made DDP-eligible.
However, one or more of its arms MAY be made DDP-eligible,
subject to the other requirements in this section.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:a7aa6a3a-2d02-4c11-bb88-0ba2eb76b0c0"
 title="Chunk Roundup">
<t>
Except in special cases (covered in
<xref target="section:d9731520-bdde-4a1b-9f54-9901d5c57648"/>),
a chunk MUST contain only one XDR data item.
This restriction makes it straightforward to reduce variable-length data items
without affecting the XDR alignment of other data items in the Payload stream.
</t>
<t>
When a sender reduces a variable-length XDR data item,
data items remaining in the Payload stream MUST remain on four-byte alignment.
Therefore, the sender always removes XDR roundup padding
for that data item from the Payload stream.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:025098f1-1355-4c97-8fda-5b4859372aa5"
 title="Read Chunks">
<t>
A "Read chunk" represents an XDR data item
that the Responder pulls from the Requester.
A Read chunk is a list of one or more RDMA read segments.
Each RDMA read segment consists of a Position field
followed by an RDMA segment, as defined in
<xref target="section:8966c401-1714-413c-9384-b1f71f0a920d"/>.
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Position:">
The byte offset in the unreduced Payload stream
where the receiver reinserts the data item conveyed in the chunk.
The Requester MUST compute the Position value
from the beginning of the unreduced Payload stream,
which begins at Position zero.
All RDMA read segments belonging to the same Read chunk
have the same value in their Position field.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
While constructing an RPC Call message,
a Requester registers memory regions containing data items
intended for RDMA Read operations.
It advertises the coordinates of these regions
by adding Read chunks to the transport header of the RPC Call message.
</t>
<t>
After receiving an RPC Call message sent via an RDMA Send operation,
a Responder transfers the chunk data from the Requester using RDMA Read operations.
The Responder inserts the first RDMA segment in a Read chunk
into the Payload stream at the byte offset indicated by its Position field.
The Responder concatenates RDMA segments
whose Position field value matches this offset
until there are no more RDMA segments at that Position value.
</t>
<t>
The Position field in an RDMA read segment
indicates where the containing Read chunk starts in the Payload stream.
The value in this field MUST be a multiple of four.
All segments in the same Read chunk share the same Position value,
even if one or more of the RDMA segments have a non-four-byte-aligned length.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:5f4cc5f7-325d-479c-b592-6e93979431d0"
 title="Decoding Read Chunks">
<t>
The Responder initiates an RDMA Read
to pull a Read chunk's data content
into registered local memory
whenever the XDR offset in the Payload stream matches that of a Read chunk.
The Responder acknowledges that it is finished with Read chunk source buffers
when it sends the corresponding RPC Reply message to the Requester.
The Requester may then release Read chunks advertised in the RPC-over-RDMA Call.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:2d24ecfa-6471-43bc-9635-872a07dbe2f8"
 title="Read Chunk Roundup">
<t>
When reducing a variable-length argument data item,
the Requester MUST NOT include
the data item's XDR roundup padding
in the chunk itself.
The chunk's total length MUST be the same as the encoded length of the data item.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:b8492157-7734-43e8-9a90-8ee32c674a12"
 title="Write Chunks">
<t>
While constructing an RPC Call message,
a Requester prepares memory regions
in which to receive DDP-eligible result data items.
A "Write chunk" represents an XDR data item
that a Responder is to push to a Requester.
It consists of an array of zero or more plain segments.
</t>
<t>
A Requester provisions Write chunks
long before the Responder has prepared the reply message.
A Requester often does not know the actual length
of the result data items to be returned,
since the result does not yet exist.
Thus, it MUST provision Write chunks large enough
to accommodate the maximum possible size of each returned data item.
</t>
<t>
Note that the XDR position of DDP-eligible data items
in the reply's Payload stream is not predictable
when a Requester constructs an RPC Call message.
Therefore, RDMA segments in a Write chunk do not have a Position field.
</t>
<t>
For each Write chunk provided by a Requester,
the Responder pushes DDP-eligible one data item to the Requester.
It fills the chunk contiguously and in segment array order
until the Responder has written that data item to the Requester in its entirety.
The Responder MUST copy the segment count
and all segments from the Requester-provided Write chunk
into the RPC Reply message's transport header.
As it does so, the Responder updates each segment length field
to reflect the actual amount of data returned in that segment.
The Responder then sends the RPC Reply message via an RDMA Send operation.
</t>
<t>
An "empty Write chunk" is a Write chunk with a zero segment count.
By definition, the length of an empty Write chunk is zero.
An "unused Write chunk" has a non-zero segment count,
but all of its segments are empty segments.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:2e73c718-e091-4d41-a88a-0b28c84fbe5c"
 title="Decoding Write Chunks">
<t>
After receiving the RPC Reply message,
the Requester reconstructs the transferred data
by concatenating the contents of each segment in array order
into the RPC Reply message's XDR stream at the known XDR position
of the associated DDP-eligible result data item.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:00f1edd4-2e2f-4b54-bc21-9d6dfa39556b"
 title="Write Chunk Roundup">
<t>
When provisioning a Write chunk for a variable-length result data item,
the Requester MUST NOT include additional space for XDR roundup padding.
A Responder MUST NOT write XDR roundup padding into a Write chunk,
even if the result is shorter than the available space in the chunk.
Therefore, when returning a single variable-length result data item,
a returned Write chunk's total length MUST be
the same as the encoded length of the result data item.
</t>
</section>

</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:740e5b29-8c88-40ab-9506-69635d9a8167"
 title="Payload Format">
<t>
Unlike RPC-over-TCP and RPC-over-UDP transports,
RPC-over-RDMA transports are aware of the XDR encoding
of each RPC message payload.
For efficiency,
the transport can convey DDP-eligible XDR data items
separately from the RPC message itself.
Also, receivers are required to post
adequate receive resources in advance of each RPC message.
</t>
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 provides several ways
to arrange conveyance of an RPC-over-RDMA message.
A sender chooses the specific format for a message
among several factors:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The existence of DDP-eligible data items in the RPC message
</t>
<t>
The size of the RPC message
</t>
<t>
The direction of the RPC message (i.e., Call or Reply)
</t>
<t>
The available hardware resources
</t>
<t>
The arrangement of source and sink memory buffers
</t>
</list>
The following subsections describe in detail how
Requesters and Responders
format RPC-over-RDMA message payloads.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:13a871a4-554f-4e3c-89ba-c5a75929f01E"
 title="Simple Format">
<t>
All RPC messages conveyed via RPC-over-RDMA version 2
require at least one RDMA Send operation to convey.
Thus, the most efficient way to send an RPC message
that is smaller than the inline threshold
is to append the Payload stream directly to the Transport stream.
When no chunks are present, senders construct Calls and Replies the same way,
and no other operations are needed.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:41c2df3b-e54d-4ccf-9eac-860f44dec2d2"
 title="Simple Format with Chunks">
<t>
If DDP-eligible data items are present in a Payload stream,
a sender MAY reduce some or all of these items,
removing them from the Payload stream.
The sender then uses a separate mechanism to transfer the reduced data items.
The Transport stream with the reduced Payload stream immediately following it
is then transferred using one RDMA Send operation.
</t>
<t>
When chunks are present,
senders construct Calls differently than Replies.
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Simple Call:">
After receiving the Transport and Payload streams
of an RPC Call message with Read chunks,
the Responder uses RDMA Read operations to move
the reduced data items contained in Read chunks.
RPC-over-RDMA Calls can carry Write chunks
for the Responder to use when sending the matching Reply.
</t>
<t hangText="Simple Reply"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
The Responder uses RDMA Write operations
to move reduced data items contained in Write chunks.
Afterward, it sends the Transport and Payload streams
of the RPC Reply message using one RDMA Send.
RPC-over-RDMA Replies always carry an empty Read chunk list.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:a690cf12-0e31-4df2-a32a-8cb8e2a3b2c8"
 title="Simple Format Examples">
<t>
<figure
 align="left"
 title="A Simple Call without chunks and
        a Simple Reply without chunks">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
        Requester                             Responder
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
       Call |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |                                     |
            |                                     | Processing
            |                                     |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   | Reply
</artwork>
</figure>
<figure
 align="left"
 title="A Simple Call with a Read chunk and
        a Simple Reply without chunks">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
        Requester                             Responder
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
       Call |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |        RDMA Read                    |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   |
            |        RDMA Response (arg data)     |
            |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |                                     |
            |                                     | Processing
            |                                     |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   | Reply
</artwork>
</figure>
<figure
 align="left"
 title="A Simple Call without chunks and
        a Simple Reply with a Write chunk">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
        Requester                             Responder
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
       Call |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |                                     |
            |                                     | Processing
            |                                     |
            |        RDMA Write (result data)     |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   | Reply
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:bda7bc14-2a3d-4224-873c-855912218987"
 title="Continued Format">
<t>
For various reasons,
a sender can choose to split a message payload
over multiple RPC-over-RDMA messages.
The Payload stream of each RPC-over-RDMA message
contains a part of the RPC message.
The receiver reconstructs the original RPC message
by concatenating in sequence the Payload stream
of each RPC-over-RDMA message.
A sender MAY split an RPC message payload on any convenient boundary.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:3b102dbf-81b2-4e0f-bb4b-d238db83ab44"
 title="Continued Format with Chunks">
<t>
If DDP-eligible data items are present in the Payload stream,
a sender MAY reduce some or all of these items,
removing them from the Payload stream.
The sender then uses a separate mechanism to transfer the reduced data items.
The Transport stream with the reduced Payload stream immediately following it
is then transferred using one RDMA Send operation.
</t>
<t>
As with Simple Format messages, when chunks are present,
senders construct Calls differently than Replies.
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Continued Call"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
After receiving the Transport and Payload streams
of an RPC Call message with Read chunks,
the Responder uses RDMA Read operations to move
the reduced data items contained in Read chunks.
RPC-over-RDMA Calls can carry Write chunks
for the Responder to use when sending the matching Reply.
</t>
<t hangText="Continued Reply"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
The Responder uses RDMA Write operations
to move reduced data items contained in Write chunks.
Afterward, it sends the Transport and Payload streams
of the RPC Reply message using multiple RDMA Sends.
RPC-over-RDMA Replies always carry an empty Read chunk list.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:49c71620-d55a-4867-801a-10928118befe"
 title="Continued Format Examples">
<t>
<figure
 align="left"
 title="A Continued Call without chunks and
        a Continued Reply without chunks">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
        Requester                             Responder
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
       Call |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |                                     |
            |                                     |
            |                                     | Processing
            |                                     |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   | Reply
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   |
</artwork>
</figure>
<figure
 align="left"
 title="A Continued Call with a Read chunk and
        a Simple Reply without chunks">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
        Requester                             Responder
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
       Call |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |        RDMA Read                    |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   |
            |        RDMA Response (arg data)     |
            |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |                                     |
            |                                     | Processing
            |                                     |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   | Reply
</artwork>
</figure>
<figure
 align="left"
 title="A Simple Call without chunks and
        a Continued Reply with a Write chunk">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
        Requester                             Responder
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
       Call |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |                                     |
            |                                     | Processing
            |                                     |
            |        RDMA Write (result data)     |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   | Reply
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   |
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:d9731520-bdde-4a1b-9f54-9901d5c57648"
 title="Special Format">
<t>
Sometimes,
after DDP-eligible data items have been removed,
a Payload stream is still too large
to send using only RDMA Send operations.
In those cases, the sender can use RDMA Read or Write operations
to convey the entire RPC message.
We refer to this as a "Special Format" message.
</t>
<t>
To transmit a Special Format message,
the sender transmits only the Transport stream
with an RDMA Send operation.
The sender does not include the Payload stream in the send buffer.
Instead, the Requester provides chunks that the Responder
uses to move the Payload stream.
</t>
<t>
Because chunks are always present in Special Format messages,
the sender always handles Calls and Replies differently.
<list style="hanging">
<t hangText="Special Call"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
The Requester provides a Read chunk
that contains the RPC Call message's Payload stream.
Every read segment in this chunk MUST contain zero (0) in its Position field.
This type of Read chunk is known as a "Position Zero Read chunk."
</t>
<t hangText="Special Reply"><vspace blankLines="0"/>
The Requester provisions a single Write chunk in advance,
known as a "Reply chunk",
in which the Responder places the RPC Reply message's Payload stream.
The Requester sizes the Reply chunk to accommodate
the maximum expected reply size for that upper-layer operation.
</t>
</list>
One purpose of a Special Format message is to handle large RPC messages.
However, Requesters MAY use a Special Format message
at any time to convey an RPC Call message.
</t>
<t>
When it has alternatives,
a Responder chooses which Format to use based on the chunks
provided by the Requester.
If a Requester provided a Write chunk
and
the Responder has a DDP-eligible result,
it first reduces the reply Payload stream.
If a Requester provided a Reply chunk
and
the reduced Payload stream is larger than the reply inline threshold,
the Responder MUST use the Requester-provided Reply chunk for the reply.
</t>
<t>
XDR data items may appear in these chunks
without regard to their DDP-eligibility.
As these chunks contain a Payload stream,
they MUST include appropriate XDR roundup padding
to maintain proper XDR alignment of their contents.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:199de5c1-e307-4664-abeb-dd687b4329c3"
 title="Special Format Examples">
<t>
<figure
 align="left"
 title="A Special Call and a Simple Reply without chunks">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
        Requester                             Responder
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_NOMSG)       |
       Call |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |        RDMA Read                    |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   |
            |        RDMA Response (RPC call)     |
            |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |                                     |
            |                                     | Processing
            |                                     |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   | Reply
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
<figure
 align="left"
 title="A Simple Call without chunks and a Special Reply">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
        Requester                             Responder
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_MSG)         |
       Call |   ------------------------------&gt;   |
            |                                     |
            |                                     | Processing
            |                                     |
            |        RDMA Write (RPC reply)       |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   |
            |        RDMA Send (RDMA_NOMSG)       |
            |   &lt;------------------------------   | Reply
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:41b8bd31-255d-4fab-a81b-df765f11ad47"
 title="Reverse-Direction Operation">

<section
 anchor="section:3816dd27-8007-47b0-82da-9d69f578f29d"
 title="Sending a Reverse-Direction RPC Call">
<t>
An RPC-over-RDMA server endpoint constructs the transport header
for a reverse-direction RPC Call as follows:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The server generates a new XID value (see
<xref target="section:97382254-b1a3-4e03-98e5-a0814b331bd0"/>
for full requirements) and places it
in the rdma_xid field of the transport header
and the xid field of the RPC Call message.
The RPC Call header MUST start with the same XID value
that is present in the transport header.
</t>
<t>
The rdma_vers field of each reverse-direction Call
MUST contain the same value as forward-direction Calls
on the same connection.
</t>
<t>
The server fills in the rdma_credits
with the credit values for the connection, as described in
<xref target="section:278fca6a-f2a8-42f3-a4e9-a8d4b217567e"/>.
</t>
<t>
The server determines the Payload format for the RPC message
and fills in the rdma_htype field as appropriate
(see Sections
<xref
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"
 target="section:740e5b29-8c88-40ab-9506-69635d9a8167"/>
and
<xref
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"
 target="section:858fef67-6100-48bc-8d3d-d46201a4b461"/>).
<xref target="section:858fef67-6100-48bc-8d3d-d46201a4b461"/>
also covers the disposition of the chunk lists.
</t>
<t>
The server MUST clear the RDMA2_F_RESPONSE flag in the rdma_flags field.
It sets the RDMA2_F_MORE flag in the rdma_flags field
as described in
<xref target="section:fb299673-74f3-4f01-adb5-26a02ccd679f"/>.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:748614a9-26da-4846-b5ff-43b06823abab"
 title="Sending a Reverse-Direction RPC Reply">
<t>
An RPC-over-RDMA server endpoint constructs the transport header
for a reverse-direction RPC Reply as follows:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The server copies the XID value from the matching RPC Call
and
places it in the rdma_xid field of the transport header
and
the xid field of the RPC Reply message.
The RPC Reply header MUST start with the same XID value
that is present in the transport header.
</t>
<t>
The rdma_vers field of each reverse-direction Call
MUST contain the same value as forward-direction Replies
on the same connection.
</t>
<t>
The server fills in the rdma_credits
with the credit values for the connection, as described in
<xref target="section:278fca6a-f2a8-42f3-a4e9-a8d4b217567e"/>.
</t>
<t>
The server determines the Payload format for the RPC message
and fills in the rdma_htype field as appropriate
(see Sections
<xref
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"
 target="section:740e5b29-8c88-40ab-9506-69635d9a8167"/>
and
<xref
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"
 target="section:858fef67-6100-48bc-8d3d-d46201a4b461"/>).
<xref target="section:858fef67-6100-48bc-8d3d-d46201a4b461"/>
also covers the disposition of the chunk lists.
</t>
<t>
The server MUST set the RDMA2_F_RESPONSE flag in the rdma_flags field.
It sets the RDMA2_F_MORE flag in the rdma_flags field
as described in
<xref target="section:fb299673-74f3-4f01-adb5-26a02ccd679f"/>.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:ed1c8ecf-360c-496f-ba93-117f016dfd4c"
 title="In the Absence of Support For Reverse-Direction Operation">
<t>
An RPC-over-RDMA transport endpoint does not
have to support reverse-direction operation.
There might be no mechanism in the transport implementation to do so.
Or, the transport implementation might support
operation in the reverse direction,
but the Upper-Layer Protocol might not yet
have configured the transport to handle reverse-direction traffic.
</t>
<t>
If an endpoint is unprepared to receive a reverse-direction message,
loss of the RDMA connection might result.
Thus a denial of service can occur if an RPC server
continues to send reverse-direction messages
after a client that is not prepared to receive them
reconnects to an endpoint.
</t>
<t>
Connection peers indicate their support for reverse-direction operation
as part of the exchange of Transport Properties
just after a connection is established (see
<xref target="section:6ace2d7f-044b-491f-97ea-5760345a2e8f"/>).
</t>
<t>
When dealing with the possibility that the remote peer
has no transport level support for reverse-direction operation,
the Upper-Layer Protocol is responsible for informing peers
when reverse direction operation is supported.
Otherwise, even a simple reverse direction RPC NULL procedure
from a peer could result in a lost connection.
Therefore, an Upper-Layer Protocol MUST NOT perform
reverse-direction RPC operations
until the RPC server indicates support for them.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:858fef67-6100-48bc-8d3d-d46201a4b461"
 title="Using Chunks During Reverse-Direction Operation">
<t>
Reverse-direction operations can use chunks,
as defined in
<xref target="section:c561e45c-fe88-47e3-bdfd-689d482fcad3"/>.
for DDP-eligible data items or in Special payload formats.
Reverse-direction chunks operate the same way
as in forward-direction operation.
Connection peers indicate their support for reverse-direction chunks
as part of the exchange of Transport Properties
just after a connection is established (see
<xref target="section:6ace2d7f-044b-491f-97ea-5760345a2e8f"/>).
</t>
<t>
However, an implementation might support
only Upper-Layer Protocols
that have no DDP-eligible data items.
Such Upper-Layer Protocols can use only small messages,
or they might have a native mechanism
for restricting the size of reverse-direction RPC messages,
obviating the need to handle chunks in the reverse direction.
</t>
<t>
When there is no Upper-Layer Protocol need
for chunks in the reverse direction,
implementers MAY choose not to provide support
for chunks in the reverse direction,
thus avoiding the complexity of implementing support
for RDMA Reads and Writes in the reverse direction.
</t>
<t>
When an RPC-over-RDMA transport implementation does not support
chunks in the reverse direction, RPC endpoints use only
the Simple Payload format without chunks
or
the Continued Payload format without chunks
to send RPC messages in the reverse direction.
</t>
<t>
If a reverse-direction Requester provides a non-empty chunk list
to a Responder that does not support chunks,
the Responder MUST report its lack of support
using one of the error values defined in
<xref target="section:87c5f543-7092-4faf-b13e-0e994e8023a7"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:328c8cb7-80db-4b24-b871-2983e9648b45"
 title="Reverse-Direction Retransmission">
<t>
In rare cases, an RPC server cannot
complete an RPC transaction
and
cannot send a Reply.
In these cases, the Requester may send the RPC transaction again
using the same RPC XID.
We refer to this as an "RPC retransmission" or a "replay."
</t>
<t>
In the forward direction,
the Requester is the RPC client.
The client is always responsible for ensuring
a transport connection is in place
before sending a dropped Call again.
</t>
<t>
With reverse-direction operation,
the Requester is an RPC server.
Because an RPC server is not responsible
for establishing transport connections with clients,
the Requester is unable to retransmit a reverse-direction Call
whenever there is no transport connection.
In this case,
the RPC server must wait for the RPC client
to re-establish a transport connection
before it can retransmit reverse-direction RPC Calls.
</t>
<t>
If the forward-direction Requester has no work to do,
it can be some time before the RPC client
re-establishes a transport connection.
An RPC server may need to abandon a waiting reverse-direction RPC Call
to avoid waiting indefinitely for the client
to re-establish a transport connection.
</t>
<t>
Therefore forward-direction Requesters SHOULD maintain a transport connection
as long as the RPC server might send reverse-direction Calls.
For example, while an NFS version 4.1 client has
open delegated files
or
active pNFS layouts,
it maintains one or more transport connections
to enable the NFS server to perform callback operations.
</t>
</section>

</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:86248e99-ca60-478a-8aff-3fb387410077"
 title="Transport Properties">
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 enables connection endpoints
to exchange information about implementation properties.
Compatible endpoints use this information to optimize data transfer.
Initially, only a small set of transport properties are defined.
The protocol provides a single message type
to exchange transport properties (see
<xref target="section:07e8c178-62df-46a7-a57e-dcf107821d93"/>).
</t>
<t>
Both the set of transport properties and the operations used
to communicate them may be extended.
Within RPC-over-RDMA version 2, such extensions are OPTIONAL.
A discussion of extending the set of transport properties appears in
<xref target="section:a355adad-f03b-41a6-94a8-4128b10301bb"/>.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:d5ac12f6-6735-48f3-b4ba-b44a19ff9298"
 title="Transport Properties Model">
<t>
The current document specifies a basic set of receiver and sender properties.
Such properties are specified using
a code point that identifies the particular transport property
and
a nominally opaque array containing the XDR encoding of the property.
</t>
<t>
The following XDR types handle transport properties:
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

typedef rpcrdma2_propid uint32;

struct rpcrdma2_propval {
        rpcrdma2_propid rdma_which;
        opaque          rdma_data&lt;&gt;;
};

typedef rpcrdma2_propval rpcrdma2_propset&lt;&gt;;

typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_propsubset&lt;&gt;;

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
The rpcrdma2_propid type specifies a distinct transport property.
The property code points are defined as const values rather than
elements in an enum type
to enable the extension by concatenating XDR definition files.
</t>
<t>
The rpcrdma2_propval type carries the value of a transport property.
The rdma_which field identifies the particular property,
and
the rdma_data field contains the associated value of that property.
A zero-length rdma_data field represents
the default value of the property specified by rdma_which.
</t>
<t>
Although the rdma_data field is opaque,
receivers interpret its contents using the XDR type
associated with the property specified by rdma_which.
When the contents of the rdma_data field
do not conform to that XDR type,
the receiver MUST return the error RDMA2_ERR_BAD_PROPVAL
using the header type RDMA2_ERROR,
as described in Section
<xref target="section:b1d23e5c-31df-483f-adb7-25430b5de38d"/>.
</t>
<t>
For example, the receiver of a message
containing a valid rpcrdma2_propval returns this error
if the length of rdma_data is greater than
the length of the transferred message.
Also, when the receiver recognizes
the rpcrdma2_propid contained in rdma_which,
it MUST report the error RDMA2_ERR_BAD_PROPVAL
if either of the following occurs:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The nominally opaque data within rdma_data is not valid when
interpreted using the property-associated typedef.
</t>
<t>
The length of rdma_data is insufficient to contain the data
represented by the property-associated typedef.
</t>
</list>
A receiver does not report an error if it does not recognize
the value contained in rdma_which.
In that case, the receiver does not process that rpcrdma2_propval.
Processing continues with the next rpcrdma2_propval, if any.
</t>
<t>
The rpcrdma2_propset type specifies a set of transport properties.
The protocol does not impose a particular ordering of the rpcrdma2_propval items within it.
</t>
<t>
The rpcrdma2_propsubset type identifies
a subset of the properties in a rpcrdma2_propset.
Each bit in the mask denotes a particular element in a previously
specified rpcrdma2_propset.
If a particular rpcrdma2_propval is at position N in the array,
then bit number N mod 32 in word N div 32 specifies whether
the defined subset includes that particular rpcrdma2_propval.
Words beyond the last one specified are assumed to contain zero.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:943010bd-c342-46b7-9fcd-df746437dd6f"
 title="Current Transport Properties">
<t>
<xref target="table:99d0e7cc-da81-4f16-9bd0-471f806bc0b6"/>
specifies a basic set of transport properties.
The columns contain the following information:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The column labeled "Property" contains a name
of the transport property described by the current row.
</t>
<t>
The column labeled "Code" specifies the code point
that identifies this property.
</t>
<t>
The column labeled "XDR type" gives the XDR type
of the data used to communicate the value of this property.
This data type overlays the data portion
of the nominally opaque rdma_data field.
</t>
<t>
The column labeled "Default" gives the default value for the property.
</t>
<t>
The column labeled "Section" indicates the section within the current
document that explains the use of this property.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<texttable
 align="left"
 style="full"
 anchor="table:99d0e7cc-da81-4f16-9bd0-471f806bc0b6">
<ttcol align="left">Property</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Code</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">XDR type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Default</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Section</ttcol>
<c>Maximum Send Size</c>
<c>1</c>
<c>uint32</c>
<c>4096</c>
<c>
<xref target="section:0a985ff5-a5c1-477f-8932-517be34ccf65"
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"/>
</c>
<c>Receive Buffer Size</c>
<c>2</c>
<c>uint32</c>
<c>4096</c>
<c>
<xref target="section:5101b1f1-b1ad-4b6b-9fa4-d6fa324ffc0d"
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"/>
</c>
<c>Maximum RDMA Segment Size</c>
<c>3</c>
<c>uint32</c>
<c>1048576</c>
<c>
<xref target="section:14ed280d-521c-410c-a190-cf891be53900"
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"/>
</c>
<c>Maximum RDMA Segment Count</c>
<c>4</c>
<c>uint32</c>
<c>16</c>
<c>
<xref target="section:98fc720d-6263-4a52-ae89-d2469b982512"
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"/>
</c>
<c>Reverse-Direction Support</c>
<c>5</c>
<c>uint32</c>
<c>0</c>
<c>
<xref target="section:6ace2d7f-044b-491f-97ea-5760345a2e8f"
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"/>
</c>
<c>Host Auth Message</c>
<c>6</c>
<c>opaque&lt;&gt;</c>
<c>N/A</c>
<c>
<xref target="section:5f63e1b6-8d24-453b-b18b-b98ad66f3671"
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"/>
</c>
</texttable>

<section
 anchor="section:0a985ff5-a5c1-477f-8932-517be34ccf65"
 title="Maximum Send Size">
<t>
The value of this property specifies
the maximum size, in octets, of Send payloads.
The endpoint receiving this value
can size its Receive buffers
based on the value of this property.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_SBSIZ = 1;
typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_prop_sbsiz;

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:5101b1f1-b1ad-4b6b-9fa4-d6fa324ffc0d"
 title="Receive Buffer Size">
<t>
The value of this property specifies
the minimum size, in octets, of pre-posted receive buffers.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_RBSIZ = 2;
typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_prop_rbsiz;

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
A sender can subsequently use this value to
determine when a message to be sent fits in
pre-posted receive buffers that the receiver has set up.
In particular:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
Requesters may use the value to determine when to provide
a Position Zero Read chunk
or
use Message Continuation
when sending a Call.
</t>
<t>
Requesters may use the value to determine when
to provide a Reply chunk when sending a Call,
based on the maximum possible size of the Reply.
</t>
<t>
Responders may use the value to determine when
to use a Reply chunk provided by the Requester,
given the actual size of a Reply.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:14ed280d-521c-410c-a190-cf891be53900"
 title="Maximum RDMA Segment Size">
<t>
The value of this property specifies
the maximum size, in octets,
of an RDMA segment this endpoint is prepared to send or receive.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_RSSIZ = 3;
typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_prop_rssiz;

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:98fc720d-6263-4a52-ae89-d2469b982512"
 title="Maximum RDMA Segment Count">
<t>
The value of this property specifies
the maximum number of RDMA segments
that can appear in a Requester's transport header.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_RCSIZ = 4;
typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_prop_rcsiz;

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:6ace2d7f-044b-491f-97ea-5760345a2e8f"
 title="Reverse-Direction Support">
<t>
The value of this property specifies
a client implementation's readiness to process
messages that are part of reverse direction RPC requests.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

const uint32 RDMA_RVRSDIR_NONE = 0;
const uint32 RDMA_RVRSDIR_SIMPLE = 1;
const uint32 RDMA_RVRSDIR_CONT = 2;
const uint32 RDMA_RVRSDIR_GENL = 3;

const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_BRS = 5;
typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_prop_brs;

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
Multiple levels of support are distinguished:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The value RDMA2_RVRSDIR_NONE indicates
that the sender does not support reverse-direction operation.
</t>
<t>
The value RDMA2_RVRSDIR_SIMPLE indicates
that the sender supports using only Simple Format messages without chunks
for reverse-direction messages.
</t>
<t>
The value RDMA2_RVRSDIR_CONT indicates
that the sender supports using either
Simple Format without chunks
or
Continued Format messages without chunks
for reverse-direction messages.
</t>
<t>
The value RDMA2_RVRSDIR_GENL indicates
that the sender supports reverse-direction messages
in the same way as forward-direction messages.
</t>
</list>
When a peer does not provide this property,
the default is the peer does not support 
reverse-direction operation.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:5f63e1b6-8d24-453b-b18b-b98ad66f3671"
 title="Host Authentication Message">
<t>
The value of this transport property enables
the exchange of host authentication material.
This property can accommodate authentication handshakes
that require multiple challenge-response interactions
and potentially large amounts of material.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_HOSTAUTH = 6;
typedef opaque rpcrdma2_prop_hostauth&lt;&gt;;

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
When this property is not present, the peer(s) remain unauthenticated.
Local security policy on each peer determines
whether the connection is permitted to continue.
</t>
</section>

</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:eef6a22e-2633-44a2-a8f0-821fec8bf824"
 title="Transport Messages">
<t>
Each transport message consists of multiple sections.
<list style="symbols">
<t>
A transport header prefix, as defined in
<xref target="section:2d1735f0-c465-43c6-9c18-3da6b7979862"/>.
Among other things, this structure indicates the header type.
</t>
<t>
The transport header proper, as defined by one of the sub-sections below.
See
<xref target="section:67b34950-5376-49fd-93d7-b4fdf80d1c9b"/>
for the mapping between header types and the corresponding header structure.
</t>
<t>
Potentially, all or part of an RPC message payload.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
This organization differs from that presented in the definition of
RPC-over-RDMA version 1
<xref target="RFC8166"/>,
which defined the first and second of the items above as a single XDR data structure.
The new organization is in keeping with RPC-over-RDMA version 2's
extensibility model, which enables the definition of new header types
without modifying the XDR definition of existing header types.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:67b34950-5376-49fd-93d7-b4fdf80d1c9b"
 title="Transport Header Types">
<t>
<xref target="table:b5c31bf9-d623-4957-97db-29fc1d416cb8"/>
lists the RPC-over-RDMA version 2 header types.
The columns contain the following information:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The column labeled "Operation" names
the particular operation.
</t>
<t>
The column labeled "Code" specifies
the value of the header type for this operation.
</t>
<t>
The column labeled "XDR type" gives
the XDR type of the data structure
used to organize the information in this new message type.
This data immediately follows the universal portion on the
transport header present in every RPC-over-RDMA transport header.
</t>
<t>
The column labeled "Msg" indicates whether this operation is
followed (or not) by an RPC message payload.
</t>
<t>
The column labeled "Section" refers to the section within the current
document that explains the use of this header type.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<texttable
 align="left"
 anchor="table:b5c31bf9-d623-4957-97db-29fc1d416cb8"
 style="full"
 suppress-title="false"
 title="">
<ttcol align="left">Operation</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Code</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">XDR type</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Msg</ttcol>
<ttcol align="left">Section</ttcol>
<c>Convey Appended RPC Message</c>
<c>0</c>
<c>rpcrdma2_msg</c>
<c>Yes</c>
<c>
<xref target="section:9af0d451-2ef3-454f-adb9-827664ccc39c"
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"/>
</c>
<c>Convey External RPC Message</c>
<c>1</c>
<c>rpcrdma2_nomsg</c>
<c>No</c>
<c>
<xref target="section:1c401555-4b7d-4e35-a9a3-8aa14228170e"
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"/>
</c>
<c>Report Transport Error</c>
<c>4</c>
<c>rpcrdma2_err</c>
<c>No</c>
<c>
<xref target="section:b1d23e5c-31df-483f-adb7-25430b5de38d"
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"/>
</c>
<c>Specify Properties at Connection</c>
<c>5</c>
<c>rpcrdma2_connprop</c>
<c>No</c>
<c>
<xref target="section:07e8c178-62df-46a7-a57e-dcf107821d93"
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"/>
</c>
</texttable>
<t>
Suppport for the operations in
<xref target="table:b5c31bf9-d623-4957-97db-29fc1d416cb8"/>
is REQUIRED.
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 implementations that receive an unrecognized header type
MUST respond with an RDMA2_ERROR message
with an rdma_err field containing RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_HTYPE
and drop the incoming message without processing it further.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:2e577c75-4e43-4e13-8b17-75afa849f0b6"
 title="Headers and Chunks">
<t>
Most RPC-over-RDMA version 2 data structures have antecedents in
corresponding structures in RPC-over-RDMA version 1.
As is typical for new versions of an existing protocol,
the XDR data structures have new names,
and there are a few small changes in content.
In some cases,
there have been structural re-organizations
to enable protocol extensibility.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:e21d4f74-b536-47f2-9d07-c03a27a20de4"
 title="Common Transport Header Prefix">
<t>
The rpcrdma_common structure defines
the initial part of each RPC-over-RDMA transport header
for RPC-over-RDMA version 2 and subsequent versions.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

struct rpcrdma_common {
             uint32         rdma_xid;
             uint32         rdma_vers;
             uint32         rdma_credit;
             uint32         rdma_htype;
};

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA version 2's use of these first four words
matches that of version 1 as required by
<xref target="RFC8166"/>.
However, there are crucial structural differences
in the XDR definition of RPC-over-RDMA version 2:
in the way that these words are described
by the respective XDR descriptions:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The header type is represented as a uint32 rather than as an enum type.
An enum would need to be modified to reflect additions to the set of
header types made by later extensions.
</t>
<t>
The header type field is part of an XDR structure devoted to
representing the transport header prefix,
rather than being part of a discriminated union,
that includes the body of each transport header type.
</t>
<t>
There is now a prefix structure
(see
<xref target="section:2d1735f0-c465-43c6-9c18-3da6b7979862"/>)
of which the rpcrdma_common structure is the initial segment.
This prefix is a newly defined XDR object within the protocol description,
which constrains the universal portion of all header types
to the four words in rpcrdma_common.
</t>
</list>
These changes are part of a more considerable structural change
in the XDR definition of RPC-over-RDMA version 2
that facilitates a cleaner treatment of protocol extension.
The XDR appearing in
<xref target="section:bf53e759-d97f-487d-a5e2-9b8153db1803"/>
reflects these changes, which
<xref target="section:d945b9f0-0666-4db7-9126-be57cf7b5f4f"/>
discusses in further detail.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:2d1735f0-c465-43c6-9c18-3da6b7979862"
 title="Transport Header Prefix">
<t>
The following prefix structure appears at the start of each
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 transport header.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

const RDMA2_F_RESPONSE           0x00000001;
const RDMA2_F_MORE               0x00000002;
const RDMA2_F_TPMORE             0x00000004;

struct rpcrdma2_hdr_prefix
        struct rpcrdma_common       rdma_start;
        uint32                      rdma_flags;
};

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
The rdma_flags field is new to RPC-over-RDMA version 2.
Currently, the only flags defined within this word are the
RDMA2_F_RESPONSE flag
and the
RDMA2_F_MORE flag.
The other flags are reserved for future use as described in
<xref target="section:55a1749d-702c-48e4-b78c-0db392692c09"/>.
The sender MUST set reserved flags to zero,
and the receiver MUST ignore reserved flags.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:4e23391c-b6a8-46b1-a399-c86f754b51bc"
 title="RDMA2_F_RESPONSE Flag">
<t>
The RDMA2_F_RESPONSE flag qualifies the value contained in the
transport header's rdma_xid field.
The RDMA2_F_RESPONSE flag enables a receiver to avoid
performing an XID lookup on incoming reverse direction Call messages.
Therefore:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
When the rdma_htype field has the value RDMA2_MSG or
RDMA2_NOMSG, the value of the RDMA2_F_RESPONSE flag MUST be the
same as the value of the associated RPC message's msg_type field.
</t>
<t>
When the header type is anything else
and
a whole or partial RPC message payload is present,
the value of the RDMA2_F_RESPONSE flag MUST be the same
as the value of the associated RPC message's msg_type field.
</t>
<t>
When no RPC message payload is present,
a Requester MUST set the value of RDMA2_F_RESPONSE
to reflect how the receiver is to interpret the
rdma_xid field.
</t>
<t>
When the rdma_htype field has the value RDMA2_ERROR,
the RDMA2_F_RESPONSE flag MUST be set.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:fb299673-74f3-4f01-adb5-26a02ccd679f"
 title="RDMA2_F_MORE Flag">
<t>
The RDMA2_F_MORE flag signifies that
the RPC-over-RDMA message payload continues in the next message.
</t>
<t>
When the sender asserts the RDMA2_F_MORE flag,
the receiver is to concatenate
the data payload of the next received message
to the end of the data payload of the received message.
The sender clears the RDMA2_F_MORE flag
in the final message in the sequence.
</t>
<t>
All RPC-over-RDMA messages in such a sequence MUST have the same values
in the rdma_xid and rdma_htype fields.
Otherwise, the receiver MUST drop the message
without processing it further.
If the receiver is a Responder, it MUST also
respond with an RDMA2_ERROR message
with the rdma_err field set to RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_CONT.
</t>
<t>
If a peer receives an RPC-over-RDMA message
with the RDMA2_F_MORE flag set,
and the rdma_htype field does not contain
the values RDMA2_MSG or RDMA2_CONNPROP,
the receiver MUST drop the message
without processing it further.
If the receiver is a Responder, it MUST also
respond with an RDMA2_ERROR message
with the rdma_err field set to RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_CONT.
</t>
<t>
The sender includes chunks only in the final message
in a sequence, in which the RDMA2_F_MORE flag is clear.
If a peer receives an RPC-over-RDMA message
with the RDMA2_F_MORE flag set, and its chunk lists are not empty,
the receiver MUST drop the message
without processing it further.
If the receiver is a Responder, it MUST also
respond with an RDMA2_ERROR message
with the rdma_err field set to RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_CONT.
</t>
<t>
There is no protocol-defined limit
on the number of concatenated messages in a sequence.
If the sender exhausts the receiver's credit grant
before sending the final message in the sequence,
the sender waits for a further credit grant
from the receiver before continuing to send messages.
</t>
<t>
Credit exhaustion can occur at the receiver
in the middle of a sequence of continued messages.
The receiver can grant more credits
by sending an RPC message payload
or an out-of-band credit grant (see
<xref target="section:f6348562-97f8-4413-96d7-bde3ff57b375"/>)
to enable the sender to send
the remaining messages in the sequence.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:1b29ba98-8a84-45be-ae09-2b1ff96e490b"
 title="RDMA2_F_TPMORE Flag">
<t>
The RDMA2_F_TPMORE flag indicates that the sender has
additional Transport Properties to send
in a subsequent RPC-over-RDMA message.
If a peer receives any message type other than RDMA2_CONNPROP
with the RDMA2_F_TPMORE flag set,
it MUST respond with an RDMA2_ERROR message type
whose rdma_err field contains RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_HTYPE,
and then silently discard the ingress message without processing it.
</t>
<t>
The RDMA2_F_TPDONE flag is clear in the final RDMA2_CONNPROP
message type from this peer on this connection.
If a peer receives an RDMA2_CONNPROP message type
after it has received an RDMA2_CONNPROP message type
with a clear RDMA2_F_TPDONE flag,
it MUST respond with an RDMA2_ERROR message type
whose rdma_err field contains RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_HTYPE,
and then silently discard the ingress message without processing it.
</t>
<t>
After both connection peers have indicated
they have finished sending their Transport Properties,
they may begin passing RPC traffic.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:af116198-1815-4308-99ab-0197b2c5ea0b"
 title="External Data Payloads">
<t>
The rpcrdma2_chunk_lists structure specifies
how explicit RDMA operations convey the message payload.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

struct rpcrdma2_chunk_lists {
        uint32                      rdma_inv_handle;
        struct rpcrdma2_read_list   *rdma_reads;
        struct rpcrdma2_write_list  *rdma_writes;
        struct rpcrdma2_write_chunk *rdma_reply;
};

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
The rdma_reads, rdma_writes, rdma_reply fields provide,
respectively, the chunks used to
read a Special Format Call
or
pull directly placed data from the Requester;
the chunks used
to push directly placed response data into the Requester's memory;
and the chunk used to push a long Reply into the Requester's memory.
See
<xref target="section:cfa8877c-b905-455d-b420-bf7a4a7f7829"/>
for further details on how a sender constructs chunks.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:a957db67-a8fd-4886-b7a7-57382cfe3190"
 title="Remote Invalidation">
<t>
A central addition relative to
the corresponding RPC-over-RDMA version 1 rdma_header structures
is the rdma_inv_handle field.
This field enables remote invalidation
of one Requester memory registration
by using the RDMA Send With Invalidate operation.
</t>
<t>
To solicit the use of Remote Invalidation,
a Requester sets the value of the rdma_inv_handle field
in an RPC Call's transport header
to a non-zero value that matches
one of the rdma_handle fields in that header.
If the Responder may invalidate none of the rdma_handle values
in the header conveying the Call,
the Requester sets the RPC Call's rdma_inv_handle field to the value zero.
</t>
<t>
If the Responder chooses not to use remote invalidation
for this particular RPC Reply,
or the RPC Call's rdma_inv_handle field contains the value zero,
the Responder simply uses RDMA Send
to transmit the matching RPC reply.
However, if the Responder chooses to use Remote Invalidation,
it uses RDMA Send With Invalidate to transmit the RPC Reply.
It MUST use the value in the corresponding Call's rdma_inv_handle field
to construct the Send With Invalidate Work Request.
</t>
<t>
A Responder MUST NOT use a Send With Invalidate Work Request when sending
an RDMA2_ERROR header type (see 
<xref target="section:b1d23e5c-31df-483f-adb7-25430b5de38d"/>),
an RDMA2_CONNPROP header type (see
<xref target="section:07e8c178-62df-46a7-a57e-dcf107821d93"/>),
or
an asynchronous credit grant (see
<xref target="section:f6348562-97f8-4413-96d7-bde3ff57b375"/>).
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:8039c7b8-9068-401e-9cbd-5c1e67d403e7"
 title="Header Types">
<t>
The header types defined and used in RPC-over-RDMA version 1
are carried over into RPC-over-RDMA version 2,
although there are some limited changes
in the definitions of existing header types:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
To simplify interoperability with RPC-over-RDMA version 1,
only the RDMA2_ERROR header (defined in
<xref target="section:b1d23e5c-31df-483f-adb7-25430b5de38d"/>)
has an XDR definition that differs from that in RPC-over-RDMA version 1,
and its modifications are all compatible extensions.
</t>
<t>
RDMA2_MSG and RDMA2_NOMSG (defined in Sections
<xref
 format="counter"
 pageno="false"
 target="section:9af0d451-2ef3-454f-adb9-827664ccc39c"/>
and
<xref
 format="counter"
 pageno="false"
 target="section:1c401555-4b7d-4e35-a9a3-8aa14228170e"/>)
have XDR definitions that match
the corresponding RPC-over-RDMA version 1 header types.
However, because of the changes to the header prefix,
the version 1 and version 2 header types differ in on-the-wire format.
</t>
<t>
RDMA2_CONNPROP (defined in
<xref target="section:07e8c178-62df-46a7-a57e-dcf107821d93"/>)
is an entirely new header type devoted to
enabling connection peers to exchange information
about their transport properties.
</t>
</list>
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:9af0d451-2ef3-454f-adb9-827664ccc39c"
 title="RDMA2_MSG: Convey RPC Message Inline">
<t>
RDMA2_MSG conveys all or part of an RPC message
immediately following the transport header in the send buffer.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

const rpcrdma2_proc RDMA2_MSG = 0;

struct rpcrdma2_msg {
        struct rpcrdma2_chunk_lists rdma_chunks;

        /* The rpc message starts here and continues
         * through the end of the transmission. */
        uint32                      rdma_rpc_first_word;
};

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:1c401555-4b7d-4e35-a9a3-8aa14228170e"
 title="RDMA2_NOMSG: Convey External RPC Message">
<t>
RDMA2_NOMSG conveys an entire RPC message payload
using explicit RDMA operations.
In particular, it is a Special Format Call
when the Responder reads the RPC payload from a memory area
specified by a Position Zero Read chunk.
It is a Special Format Reply
when the Responder writes the RPC payload into a memory area
specified by a Reply chunk.
In both cases, the sender sets the rdma_xid field
to the same value as the xid of the RPC message payload.
</t>
<t>
If all the chunk lists are empty
the message conveys a credit grant refresh.
The header prefix of this message contains a credit grant refresh
in the rdma_credit field.
In this case, the sender MUST set the rdma_xid field to zero.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

const rpcrdma2_proc RDMA2_NOMSG = 1;

struct rpcrdma2_nomsg {
        struct rpcrdma2_chunk_lists rdma_chunks;
};

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
In RPC-over-RDMA version 2,
a sender should use Message Continuation
as an alternative to using a Special Format message.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:b1d23e5c-31df-483f-adb7-25430b5de38d"
 title="RDMA2_ERROR: Report Transport Error">
<t>
RDMA2_ERROR reports a transport layer error on a previous transmission.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

const rpcrdma2_proc RDMA2_ERROR = 4;

struct rpcrdma2_err_vers {
        uint32 rdma_vers_low;
        uint32 rdma_vers_high;
};

struct rpcrdma2_err_write {
        uint32 rdma_chunk_index;
        uint32 rdma_length_needed;
};

union rpcrdma2_error switch (rpcrdma2_errcode rdma_err) {
        case RDMA2_ERR_VERS:
          rpcrdma2_err_vers rdma_vrange;
        case RDMA2_ERR_READ_CHUNKS:
          uint32 rdma_max_chunks;
        case RDMA2_ERR_WRITE_CHUNKS:
          uint32 rdma_max_chunks;
        case RDMA2_ERR_SEGMENTS:
          uint32 rdma_max_segments;
        case RDMA2_ERR_WRITE_RESOURCE:
          rpcrdma2_err_write rdma_writeres;
        case RDMA2_ERR_REPLY_RESOURCE:
          uint32 rdma_length_needed;
        default:
          void;
};

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
See
<xref target="section:995a7597-4e89-48c3-b142-35b783ef1329"/>
for details on the use of this header type.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:07e8c178-62df-46a7-a57e-dcf107821d93"
 title="RDMA2_CONNPROP: Exchange Transport Properties">
<t>
The RDMA2_CONNPROP message type enables a connection peer
to publish the properties of its implementation to its
remote peer.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

struct rpcrdma2_connprop {
        rpcrdma2_propset rdma_props;
};

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
Each peer sends an RDMA2_CONNPROP message type
as the first message after the client has established a connection.
The size of this initial message is limited
to the default inline threshold for the RPC-over-RDMA version that is in effect.
If a peer has more or larger Transport Properties than can fit
in the initial RDMA2_CONNPROP message type,
it sets the RDMA2_F_TPMORE flag.
The final RDMA2_CONNPROP message type the peer sends on that connection
must have a clear RDMA2_F_TPMORE flag.
</t>
<t>
A peer may encounter properties that it does not recognize or support.
In such cases, the receiver ignores unsupported properties
without generating an error response.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:19fc8c94-d83f-4c1b-8ce3-700918d129b5"
 title="Choosing a Reply Mechanism">
<t>
A Requester provisions all necessary registered memory resources
for both an RPC Call and its matching RPC Reply.
A Requester constructs each RPC Call, thus it can compute
the exact memory resources needed to send every Call.
However, the Requester allocates memory resources
to receive the corresponding Reply before the Responder has constructed it.
Occasionally, it is challenging for the Requester
to know in advance precisely what resources are needed to receive the Reply.
</t>
<t>
In RPC-over-RDMA version 2,
a Requester can provide a Reply chunk for any transaction.
The Responder can use the provided Reply chunk
or
it can decide to use another means to convey the RPC Reply.
If
the combination of the provided Write chunk list
and
Reply chunk
is not adequate to convey a Reply,
the Responder SHOULD use Message Continuation (see
<xref target="section:fb299673-74f3-4f01-adb5-26a02ccd679f"/>)
to send that Reply.
If even that is not possible,
the Responder sends an RDMA2_ERROR message to the Requester,
as described in
<xref target="section:b1d23e5c-31df-483f-adb7-25430b5de38d"/>:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
If the Write chunk list cannot accommodate the ULP's DDP-eligible data payload,
the Responder sends an RDMA2_ERR_WRITE_RESOURCE error.
</t>
<t>
If the Reply chunk cannot accommodate the parts of the Reply that are not DDP-eligible,
the Responder sends an RDMA2_ERR_REPLY_RESOURCE error.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
When receiving such errors,
the Requester can retry the ULP call using more substantial reply resources.
In cases where retrying the ULP request is not possible
(e.g., the request is non-idempotent),
the Requester terminates the RPC transaction
and presents an error to the RPC consumer.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:995a7597-4e89-48c3-b142-35b783ef1329"
 title="Error Handling">
<t>
A receiver performs validity checks on ingress RPC-over-RDMA messages
before it passes the conveyed RPC message to the RPC layer.
For example, if an ingress message is not as long as
the size of struct rpcrdma2_hdr_prefix (20 octets),
the receiver cannot trust the value of the rdma_xid field.
In this case, the receiver MUST silently discard the ingress message
without processing it further, and without a response to the sender.
</t>
<t>
However, in many other cases, the receiver needs to actively report
a problem with the RPC-over-RDMA message to its sender.
The RDMA2_ERROR message type is used for this purpose.
To form an RDMA2_ERROR message type:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The rdma_xid field MUST contain the same XID
that was in the rdma_xid field in the ingress request.
</t>
<t>
The rdma_vers field MUST contain the same version
that was in the rdma_vers field in the ingress request.
</t>
<t>
The sender sets the rdma_credit field to the credit values in effect
for this connection.
</t>
<t>
The rdma_htype field MUST contain the value RDMA2_ERROR.
</t>
<t>
The rdma_err field contains a value
that reflects the type of error that occurred,
as described in the subsections below.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
When a peer receives an RDMA2_ERROR message type
with an unrecognized or unsupported value in its rdma_err field,
it MUST silently discard the message without processing it further.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:c445fd74-d6c2-4f64-a215-844c84da4b6b"
 title="Basic Transport Stream Parsing Errors">

<section
 anchor="section:4a5e9013-9c26-4776-afbd-95318cb2ea8a"
 title="RDMA2_ERR_VERS">
<t>
When a Responder detects an RPC-over-RDMA header version
that it does not support
(the current document defines version 2),
it MUST respond with an RDMA2_ERROR message type
and
set its rdma_err field to RDMA2_ERR_VERS.
The Responder then fills in the rpcrdma2_err_vers structure
with the RPC-over-RDMA versions it supports.
The Responder MUST silently discard the ingress message
without passing it to the RPC layer
</t>
<t>
When a Requester receives this error,
it uses the information in the rpcrdma2_err_vers structure
to select an RPC-over-RDMA version that both peers support.
A Requester MUST NOT subsequently send a message that uses
a version that the Responder has indciated it does not support.
RDMA2_ERR_VERS indicates a permanent error.
Receipt of this error completes the RPC transaction
associated with XID in the rdma_xid field.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:9754ea3a-d237-41cf-9739-99843e11e524"
 title="RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_HTYPE">
<t>
If a Responder recognizes the value in an ingress rdma_vers field,
but it does not recognize the value in the rdma_htype field
or
does not support that header type,
it MUST set the rdma_err field to RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_HTYPE.
The Responder MUST silently discard the incoming message
without passing it to the RPC layer.
</t>
<t>
A Requester MUST NOT subsequently send a message that uses
an htype that the Responder has indicated it does not support.
RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_HTYPE indicates a permanent error.
Receipt of this error completes the RPC transaction
associated with XID in the rdma_xid field.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:37afd7d4-5d72-4300-ad6d-95558cdd5e19"
 title="RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_CONT">
<t>
If a Responder detects a problem with an ingress RPC-over-RDMA message
that is part of a Message Continuation sequence,
the Responder MUST set the rdma_err field to RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_CONT.
<xref target="section:fb299673-74f3-4f01-adb5-26a02ccd679f"/>
discusses the types of problems to watch for.
The Responder MUST silently discard all ingress messages
with an rdma_xid field that matches the failing message
without reassembling the payload.
</t>
<t>
RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_CONT indicates a permanent error.
Receipt of this error completes the RPC transaction
associated with XID in the rdma_xid field.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:932d8a55-30e3-412c-8b78-355606742861"
 title="XDR Errors">
<t>
A receiver might encounter an XDR parsing error that
prevents it from processing an ingress Transport stream.
Examples of such errors include:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
An invalid value in the rdma_proc field.
</t>
<t>
An RDMA_NOMSG message where the
Read list,
Write list,
and
Reply chunk are marked not present.
</t>
<t>
The value of the rdma_xid field does not match
the value of the XID field in the accompanying RPC
message.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
When a Responder receives a valid RPC-over-RDMA header
but the Responder's ULP implementation cannot parse the RPC arguments
in the RPC Call,
the Responder returns an RPC Reply with status GARBAGE_ARGS,
using an RDMA2_MSG message type.
This type of parsing failure might be due to mismatches
between chunk sizes or offsets
and
the contents of the Payload stream, for example.
In this case, the error is permanent,
but the Requester has no way to know how much processing
the Responder has completed for this RPC transaction.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:90449e5c-e65a-48c0-80bf-e9080d67094e"
 title="RDMA2_ERR_BAD_XDR">
<t>
If a Responder recognizes the values in the rdma_vers field,
but it cannot otherwise parse the ingress Transport stream,
it MUST set the rdma_err field to RDMA2_ERR_BAD_XDR.
The Responder MUST silently discard the ingress message
without passing it to the RPC layer.
</t>
<t>
RDMA2_ERR_BAD_XDR indicates a permanent error.
Receipt of this error completes the RPC transaction
associated with XID in the rdma_xid field.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="secction:4a3d9ac4-4083-46d1-99b4-76a0b1ac93bf"
 title="RDMA2_ERR_BAD_PROPVAL">
<t>
If a receiver recognizes the value in an ingress rdma_which field,
but it cannot parse the accompanying propval,
it MUST set the rdma_err field to RDMA2_ERR_BAD_PROPVAL (see
<xref target="section:d5ac12f6-6735-48f3-b4ba-b44a19ff9298"/>).
The receiver MUST silently discard the ingress message
without applying any of its property settings.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:87c5f543-7092-4faf-b13e-0e994e8023a7"
 title="Responder RDMA Operational Errors">
<t>
In RPC-over-RDMA version 2,
the Responder initiates RDMA Read and Write operations
that target the Requester's memory.
Problems might arise as the Responder attempts
to use Requester-provided resources for RDMA operations.
For example:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
Usually, chunks can be validated only by using their contents to perform data transfers.
If chunk contents are invalid
(e.g., a memory region is no longer registered
or
a chunk length exceeds the end of the registered memory region),
a Remote Access Error occurs.
</t>
<t>If a Requester's Receive buffer is too small,
the Responder's Send operation completes with a Local Length Error.
</t>
<t>
If the Requester-provided Reply chunk is too small
to accommodate a large RPC Reply message,
a Remote Access Error occurs.
A Responder might detect this problem before attempting to write past the end of the Reply chunk.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
RDMA operational errors can be fatal to the connection.
To avoid a retransmission loop and repeated connection loss that deadlocks the connection,
once the Requester has re-established a connection,
the Responder should send an RDMA2_ERROR response
to indicate that no RPC-level reply is possible for that transaction.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:77a9225b-7b43-4899-b9d1-5df14310a144"
 title="RDMA2_ERR_READ_CHUNKS">
<t>
If a Requester presents more DDP-eligible arguments
than a Responder is prepared to Read,
the Responder MUST
set the rdma_err field to RDMA2_ERR_READ_CHUNKS
and
set the rdma_max_chunks field
to the maximum number of Read chunks the Responder can process.
If the Responder implementation cannot handle any Read chunks for a request,
it MUST set the rdma_max_chunks to zero in this response.
The Responder MUST silently discard the ingress message
without processing it further.
</t>
<t>
The Requester can reconstruct the Call using
Message Continuation
or
a Special Format payload
and resend it.
If the Requester does not resend the Call,
it MUST terminate this RPC transaction with an error.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:61617957-ee18-4d10-bf47-3b932739eee4"
 title="RDMA2_ERR_WRITE_CHUNKS">
<t>
If a Requester has constructed an RPC Call
with more DDP-eligible results than
the Responder is prepared to Write,
the Responder MUST set the rdma_err field to RDMA2_ERR_WRITE_CHUNKS
and
set the rdma_max_chunks field
to the maximum number of Write chunks the Responder can return.
The Requester can reconstruct the Call
with no Write chunks
and
a Reply chunk of appropriate size.
If the Requester does not resend the Call,
it MUST terminate this RPC transaction with an error.
</t>
<t>
If the Responder implementation cannot handle any Write chunks
for a request
and
cannot send the Reply using Message Continuation,
it MUST return a response of RDMA2_ERR_REPLY_RESOURCE instead (see below).
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:ff471562-5a8f-4dbd-8f37-ac41c5587b93"
 title="RDMA2_ERR_SEGMENTS">
<t>
If a Requester has constructed an RPC Call
with a chunk that contains more segments than the Responder supports,
the Responder MUST
set the rdma_err field to RDMA2_ERR_SEGMENTS
and
set the rdma_max_segments field
to the maximum number of segments the Responder can process.
The Requester can reconstruct the Call and resend it.
If the Requester does not resend the Call,
it MUST terminate this RPC transaction with an error.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:229512aa-cd65-4d5e-b66e-65a4ed3731cc"
 title="RDMA2_ERR_WRITE_RESOURCE">
<t>
If a Requester has provided a Write chunk
that is not large enough to contain a DDP-eligible result,
the Responder MUST set the rdma_err field to RDMA2_ERR_WRITE_RESOURCE.
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
The Responder MUST set the rdma_chunk_index field
to point to the first Write chunk in the transport header
that is too short,
or to zero to indicate that it was not possible
to determine which chunk is too small.
Indexing starts at one (1), which represents the first Write chunk.
The Responder MUST set the rdma_length_needed to the number of bytes
needed in that chunk to convey the result data item.
</t>
<t>
The Requester can reconstruct the Call with more reply resources
and resend it.
If the Requester does not resend the Call
(for instance, if the Responder set the index and length fields to zero),
it MUST terminate this RPC transaction with an error.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:7b2d20ad-072e-4b9c-8a16-e9a28009ae6b"
 title="RDMA2_ERR_REPLY_RESOURCE">
<t>
If a Responder cannot send an RPC Reply
using Message Continuation
and
the Reply does not fit in the Reply chunk,
the Responder MUST set the rdma_err field to RDMA2_ERR_REPLY_RESOURCE.
The Responder MUST set the rdma_length_needed
to the number of Reply chunk bytes needed to convey the reply.
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
The Requester can reconstruct the Call with more reply resources
and resend it.
If the Requester does not resend the Call
(for instance, if the Responder set the length field to zero),
it MUST terminate this RPC transaction with an error.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:125537e3-1b73-465f-9602-c3986df297d6"
 title="Other Operational Errors">
<t>
While a Requester is constructing an RPC Call message,
an unrecoverable problem might occur
that prevents the Requester from posting further RDMA Work Requests on behalf of that message.
As with other transports,
if a Requester is unable to construct and transmit an RPC Call,
the associated RPC transaction fails immediately.
</t>
<t>
After a Requester has received a Reply,
if it is unable to invalidate a memory region due to an unrecoverable problem,
the Requester MUST close the connection to protect that memory
from Responder access before the associated RPC transaction is complete.
</t>
<t>
While a Responder is constructing an RPC Reply message or error message,
an unrecoverable problem might occur that prevents the Responder
from posting further RDMA Work Requests on behalf of that message.
If a Responder is unable to construct and transmit
an RPC Reply
or
RPC-over-RDMA error message,
the Responder MUST close the connection
to signal to the Requester that a reply was lost.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:8a40d281-66fb-4f61-a686-190624aa4001"
 title="RDMA2_ERR_SYSTEM">
<t>
If some problem occurs on a Responder
that does not fit into the above categories,
the Responder MAY report it to the Requester
by setting the rdma_err field to RDMA2_ERR_SYSTEM.
The Responder MUST silently discard the message(s)
associated with the failing transaction
without further processing.
</t>
<t>
RDMA2_ERR_SYSTEM is a permanent error.
This error does not indicate
how much of the transaction the Responder has processed,
nor does it indicate a particular recovery action for the Requester.
A Requester that receives this error MUST terminate the RPC transaction
associated with the XID value in the RDMA2_ERROR message's rdma_xid field.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:1b7beb7d-b694-4309-95ee-f81a05637ef6"
 title="RDMA Transport Errors">
<t>
The RDMA connection and physical link
provide some degree of error detection and retransmission.
iWARP's Marker PDU Aligned (MPA) layer (when used over TCP),
the Stream Control Transmission Protocol (SCTP),
as well as the InfiniBand link layer
<xref target="IBA"/>
all provide Cyclic Redundancy Check (CRC) protection of RDMA payloads.
CRC-class protection is a general attribute of such transports.
</t>
<t>
Additionally, the RPC layer itself can accept errors
from the transport and recover via retransmission.
RPC recovery can typically handle
complete loss and re-establishment of a transport connection.
</t>
<t>
The details of reporting and recovery from RDMA link-layer errors
are described in
specific link-layer APIs and operational specifications
and are outside the scope of this protocol specification.
See
<xref
 target="section:912a2c09-95ec-4cb6-aa2b-2245726d9edf"/>
for further discussion of RPC-level integrity schemes.
</t>
</section>

</section>



<section
 anchor="section:bf53e759-d97f-487d-a5e2-9b8153db1803"
 title="XDR Protocol Definition">
<t>
This section contains a description of the core features
of the RPC-over-RDMA version 2 protocol
expressed in the XDR language
<xref target="RFC4506"/>.
It organizes the description to make it simple
to extract into a form that is
ready to compile
or
combine with similar descriptions published later
as extensions to RPC-over-RDMA version 2.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:aaab9699-eae3-46ca-a1d5-a8776a5ecb7d"
 title="Code Component License">
<t>
Code Components extracted from the current document
must include the following license text.
When combining the extracted XDR code
with other XDR code which has an identical license,
only a single copy of the license text needs to be retained.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

/// /*
///  * Copyright (c) 2010-2018 IETF Trust and the persons
///  * identified as authors of the code.  All rights reserved.
///  *
///  * The authors of the code are:
///  * B. Callaghan, T. Talpey, C. Lever, and D. Noveck.
///  *
///  * Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with
///  * or without modification, are permitted provided that the
///  * following conditions are met:
///  *
///  * - Redistributions of source code must retain the above
///  *   copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
///  *   following disclaimer.
///  *
///  * - Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above
///  *   copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
///  *   following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other
///  *   materials provided with the distribution.
///  *
///  * - Neither the name of Internet Society, IETF or IETF
///  *   Trust, nor the names of specific contributors, may be
///  *   used to endorse or promote products derived from this
///  *   software without specific prior written permission.
///  *
///  *   THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS
///  *   AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED
///  *   WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE
///  *   IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS
///  *   FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED.  IN NO
///  *   EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE
///  *   LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL,
///  *   EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT
///  *   NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR
///  *   SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS
///  *   INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF
///  *   LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY,
///  *   OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING
///  *   IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF
///  *   ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
///  */
///

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:a288b3e6-5e73-412d-91e8-f87c031cb05b"
 title="Extraction of the XDR Definition">
<t>
Implementers can apply the following sed script
to the current document to produce
a machine-readable XDR description
of the base RPC-over-RDMA version 2 protocol.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

sed -n -e 's:^ */// ::p' -e 's:^ *///$::p'

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
That is, if this document is in a file called "spec.txt",
then implementers can do the following
to extract an XDR description file
and store it in the file rpcrdma-v2.x.
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

sed -n -e 's:^ */// ::p' -e 's:^ *///$::p' \
     &lt; spec.txt &gt; rpcrdma-v2.x

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
Although this file is a usable description of the base protocol,
when extensions are to be supported,
it may be desirable to divide the description into multiple files.
The following script achieves that purpose:
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;

#!/usr/local/bin/perl
open(IN,"rpcrdma-v2.x");
open(OUT,"&gt;temp.x");
while(&lt;IN&gt;)
{
  if (m/FILE ENDS: (.*)$/)
    {
      close(OUT);
      rename("temp.x", $1);
      open(OUT,"&gt;temp.x");
    }
    else
    {
      print OUT $_;
    }
}
close(IN);
close(OUT);

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
Running the above script results in two files:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The file common.x, containing the license
plus the shared XDR definitions
that need to be made available
to both the base protocol and any subsequent extensions.
</t>
<t>
The file baseops.x containing the XDR definitions
for the base protocol defined in this document.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Extensions to RPC-over-RDMA version 2,
published as Standards Track documents,
should have similarly structured XDR definitions.
Once an implementer has extracted
the XDR for all desired extensions
and
the base XDR definition contained in the current document,
she can concatenate them to produce
a consolidated XDR definition
that reflects the set of extensions
selected for her RPC-over-RDMA version 2 implementation.
</t>
<t>
Alternatively, the XDR descriptions can be compiled separately.
In that case, the combination of common.x and baseops.x
defines the base transport.
The combination of common.x and the XDR description
of each extension produces a full XDR definition of that extension.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:b25ffcfc-511f-4383-8025-4a68cfcb4f49"
 title="XDR Definition for RPC-over-RDMA Version 2 Core Structures">
<t>
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
/// /*******************************************************************
///  *    Transport Header Prefixes
///  ******************************************************************/
///
/// struct rpcrdma_common {
///         uint32         rdma_xid;
///         uint32         rdma_vers;
///         uint32         rdma_credit;
///         uint32         rdma_htype;
/// };
///
/// const RDMA2_F_RESPONSE           0x00000001;
/// const RDMA2_F_MORE               0x00000002;
/// const RDMA2_F_TPMORE             0x00000004;
///
/// struct rpcrdma2_hdr_prefix
///         struct rpcrdma_common       rdma_start;
///         uint32                      rdma_flags;
/// };
///
/// /*******************************************************************
///  *    Chunks and Chunk Lists
///  ******************************************************************/
///
/// struct rpcrdma2_segment {
///         uint32 rdma_handle;
///         uint32 rdma_length;
///         uint64 rdma_offset;
/// };
///
/// struct rpcrdma2_read_segment {
///         uint32                  rdma_position;
///         struct rpcrdma2_segment rdma_target;
/// };
///
/// struct rpcrdma2_read_list {
///         struct rpcrdma2_read_segment rdma_entry;
///         struct rpcrdma2_read_list    *rdma_next;
/// };
///
/// struct rpcrdma2_write_chunk {
///         struct rpcrdma2_segment rdma_target&lt;&gt;;
/// };
///
/// struct rpcrdma2_write_list {
///         struct rpcrdma2_write_chunk rdma_entry;
///         struct rpcrdma2_write_list  *rdma_next;
/// };
///
/// struct rpcrdma2_chunk_lists {
///         uint32                      rdma_inv_handle;
///         struct rpcrdma2_read_list   *rdma_reads;
///         struct rpcrdma2_write_list  *rdma_writes;
///         struct rpcrdma2_write_chunk *rdma_reply;
/// };
///
/// /*******************************************************************
///  *    Transport Properties
///  ******************************************************************/
///
/// /*
///  * Types for transport properties model
///  */
/// typedef rpcrdma2_propid uint32;
///
/// struct rpcrdma2_propval {
///         rpcrdma2_propid rdma_which;
///         opaque          rdma_data&lt;&gt;;
/// };
///
/// typedef rpcrdma2_propval rpcrdma2_propset&lt;&gt;;
/// typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_propsubset&lt;&gt;;
///
/// /*
///  * Transport propid values for basic properties
///  */
/// const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_SBSIZ = 1;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_RBSIZ = 2;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_RSSIZ = 3;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_RCSIZ = 4;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_BRS = 5;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_PROPID_HOSTAUTH = 6;
///
/// /*
///  * Types specific to particular properties
///  */
/// typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_prop_sbsiz;
/// typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_prop_rbsiz;
/// typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_prop_rssiz;
/// typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_prop_rcsiz;
/// typedef uint32 rpcrdma2_prop_brs;
/// typedef opaque rpcrdma2_prop_hostauth&lt;&gt;;
///
/// const uint32 RDMA2_RVRSDIR_NONE = 0;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_RVRSDIR_SIMPLE = 1;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_RVRSDIR_CONT = 1;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_RVRSDIR_GENL = 3;
///
/// /* FILE ENDS: common.x; */

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:84e950a5-c842-4d19-b56d-0458c3e219b2"
 title="XDR Definition for RPC-over-RDMA Version 2 Base Header Types">
<t>
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;
/// /*******************************************************************
///  *    Descriptions of RPC-over-RDMA Header Types
///  ******************************************************************/
///
/// /*
///  * Header Type Codes.
///  */
/// const rpcrdma2_proc RDMA2_MSG = 0;
/// const rpcrdma2_proc RDMA2_NOMSG = 1;
/// const rpcrdma2_proc RDMA2_ERROR = 4;
/// const rpcrdma2_proc RDMA2_CONNPROP = 5;
///
/// /*
///  * Header Types to Convey RPC Messages.
///  */
/// struct rpcrdma2_msg {
///         struct rpcrdma2_chunk_lists rdma_chunks;
///
///         /* The rpc message starts here and continues
///          * through the end of the transmission. */
///         uint32                      rdma_rpc_first_word;
/// };
///
/// struct rpcrdma2_nomsg {
///         struct rpcrdma2_chunk_lists rdma_chunks;
/// };
///
/// /*
///  * Header Type to Report Errors.
///  */
/// const uint32 RDMA2_ERR_VERS = 1;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_ERR_BAD_XDR = 2;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_ERR_BAD_PROPVAL = 3;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_HTYPE = 4;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_ERR_INVAL_CONT = 5;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_ERR_READ_CHUNKS = 6;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_ERR_WRITE_CHUNKS = 7;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_ERR_SEGMENTS = 8;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_ERR_WRITE_RESOURCE = 9;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_ERR_REPLY_RESOURCE = 10;
/// const uint32 RDMA2_ERR_SYSTEM = 100;
///
/// struct rpcrdma2_err_vers {
///         uint32 rdma_vers_low;
///         uint32 rdma_vers_high;
/// };
///
/// struct rpcrdma2_err_write {
///         uint32 rdma_chunk_index;
///         uint32 rdma_length_needed;
/// };
///
/// union rpcrdma2_error switch (rpcrdma2_errcode rdma_err) {
///         case RDMA2_ERR_VERS:
///           rpcrdma2_err_vers rdma_vrange;
///         case RDMA2_ERR_READ_CHUNKS:
///           uint32 rdma_max_chunks;
///         case RDMA2_ERR_WRITE_CHUNKS:
///           uint32 rdma_max_chunks;
///         case RDMA2_ERR_SEGMENTS:
///           uint32 rdma_max_segments;
///         case RDMA2_ERR_WRITE_RESOURCE:
///           rpcrdma2_err_write rdma_writeres;
///         case RDMA2_ERR_REPLY_RESOURCE:
///           uint32 rdma_length_needed;
///         default:
///           void;
/// };
///
/// /*
///  * Header Type to Exchange Transport Properties.
///  */
/// struct rpcrdma2_connprop {
///         rpcrdma2_propset rdma_props;
/// };
///
/// /* FILE ENDS: baseops.x; */

&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:5541f0da-efbb-4431-af9c-6f82aa773963"
 title="Use of the XDR Description">
<t>
The files common.x and baseops.x,
when combined with the XDR descriptions for extension defined later,
produce a human-readable and compilable description
of the RPC-over-RDMA version 2 protocol with the included extensions.
</t>
<t>
Although this XDR description can generate encoders and decoders
for the Transport and Payload streams,
there are elements of the operation of RPC-over-RDMA version 2
that cannot be expressed within the XDR language.
Implementations that use the output of an automated XDR processor
need to provide additional code to bridge these gaps.
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The Transport stream is not a single XDR object.
Instead, the header prefix is one XDR data item,
and the rest of the header is a separate XDR data item.
<xref target="table:b5c31bf9-d623-4957-97db-29fc1d416cb8"/>
expresses the mapping between the header type in the header prefix
and
the XDR object representing the header type.
</t>
<t>
The relationship between
the Transport stream
and
the Payload stream
is not specified using XDR.
Comments within the XDR text
make clear where transported messages,
described by their own XDR definitions,
need to appear.
Such data is opaque to the transport.
</t>
<t>
Continuation of RPC messages across transport message boundaries
requires that message assembly facilities
not specifiable within XDR are part of transport implementations.
</t>
<t>
Transport properties are constant integer values.
<xref target="table:99d0e7cc-da81-4f16-9bd0-471f806bc0b6"/>
expresses the mapping between
each property's code point
and
the XDR typedef that represents the structure of the property's value.
XDR does not possess the facility to express that mapping in an extensible way.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
The role of XDR in RPC-over-RDMA specifications
is more limited than for protocols
where the totality of the protocol is expressible within XDR.
XDR lacks the facility to represent
the embedding of XDR-encoded payload material.
Also, the need to cleanly accommodate extensions
has meant that those using rpcgen in their applications
need to take an active role to provide
the facilities that cannot be expressed within XDR.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:e914de0a-05f3-4e14-a067-fb49a4f9b0ad"
 title="RPC Bind Parameters">
<t>
Before establishing a new connection,
an RPC client obtains a transport address for the RPC server.
The means used to obtain this address
and to open an RDMA connection is dependent
on the type of RDMA transport
and is the responsibility of each RPC protocol binding
and its local implementation.
</t>
<t>
RPC services typically register with a portmap or rpcbind service
<xref target="RFC1833"/>,
which associates an RPC Program number with a service address.
This policy is no different with RDMA transports.
However, a distinct service address (port number)
is sometimes required for operation on RPC-over-RDMA.
</t>
<t>
When mapped atop the iWARP transport
<xref target="RFC5040"/>
<xref target="RFC5041"/>,
which uses IP port addressing due to its layering on TCP or SCTP,
port mapping is trivial
and consists merely of issuing the port in the connection process.
The NFS/RDMA protocol service
address has been assigned port 20049 by IANA, for both iWARP/TCP and
iWARP/SCTP <xref target="RFC8267"/>.
</t>
<t>
When mapped atop InfiniBand
<xref target="IBA"/>,
which uses a service endpoint naming scheme based on a Group Identifier (GID),
a translation MUST be employed.
One such translation is described in
Annexes A3 (Application Specific Identifiers),
A4 (Sockets Direct Protocol (SDP)),
and A11 (RDMA IP CM Service) of
<xref target="IBA"/>,
which is appropriate for translating IP port addressing
to the InfiniBand network.
Therefore, in this case,
IP port addressing may be readily employed by the upper layer.
</t>
<t>
When a mapping standard or convention exists
for IP ports on an RDMA interconnect,
there are several possibilities for each upper layer to consider:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
One possibility is to have the server register
its mapped IP port with the rpcbind service
under the netid (or netids) defined in
<xref target="RFC8166"/>.
An RPC-over-RDMA-aware RPC client can then
resolve its desired service to a mappable port
and
proceed to connect.
This method is the most flexible and compatible approach
for those upper layers that are defined to use the rpcbind service.
</t>
<t>
A second possibility is to have the RPC server's portmapper
register itself on the RDMA interconnect at a "well-known" service address
(on UDP or TCP, this corresponds to port 111).
An RPC client can connect to this service address
and
use the portmap protocol to obtain a service address
in response to a program number
(e.g., an iWARP port number or an InfiniBand GID).
</t>
<t>
Alternately, an RPC client can connect
to the mapped well-known port for the service itself,
if it is appropriately defined.
By convention, the NFS/RDMA service,
when operating atop such an InfiniBand fabric,
uses the same 20049 assignment as for iWARP.
</t>
</list>
Historically, different RPC protocols have taken different approaches
to their port assignments.
The current document leaves the specific method for each RPC-over-RDMA-enabled ULB.
</t>
<t>
<xref target="RFC8166"/>
defines two new netid values
to be used for registration of upper layers
atop iWARP
<xref target="RFC5040"/> <xref target="RFC5041"/>
and (when a suitable port translation service is available) InfiniBand
<xref target="IBA"/>.
Additional RDMA-capable networks MAY define their own netids,
or if they provide a port translation,
they MAY share the one defined in
<xref target="RFC8166"/>.
</t>
</section>

<!-- RFC Editor:
Please remove the following section and the reference to RFC 7942
before this document is published.
-->

<section
 anchor="section:fd2f45e7-85fa-4863-a4cd-ea200878062f"
 title="Implementation Status">
<t>
This section records the status of known implementations of the protocol
defined by this specification at the time of posting of this Internet-Draft,
and is based on a proposal described in
<xref target="RFC7942"/>.
The description of implementations in this section is intended to
assist the IETF in its decision processes in progressing drafts to RFCs.
</t>
<t>
Please note that the listing of any individual implementation here
does not imply endorsement by the IETF.
Furthermore, no effort has been spent to verify the information presented here
that was supplied by IETF contributors.
This is not intended as, and must not be construed to be,
a catalog of available implementations or their features.
Readers are advised to note that other implementations may exist.
</t>
<t>
At this time, no known implementations of the protocol
described in the current document exist.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:912a2c09-95ec-4cb6-aa2b-2245726d9edf"
 title="Security Considerations">

<section
 anchor="section:9e0f4573-2f3e-4758-9a9d-c5ae8f54d5f6"
 title="Memory Protection">
<t>
A primary consideration is the protection of the integrity and confidentiality
of host memory by an RPC-over-RDMA transport.
The use of an RPC-over-RDMA transport protocol MUST NOT introduce vulnerabilities
to system memory contents nor memory owned by user processes.
Any RDMA provider used for RPC transport MUST conform
to the requirements of
<xref target="RFC5042"/>
to satisfy these protections.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:2ca69bb1-1d40-4226-a375-face55cf0108"
 title="Protection Domains">
<t>
The use of a Protection Domain to limit the exposure of memory regions
to a single connection is critical.
Any attempt by an endpoint not participating in that connection
to reuse memory handles needs to result in immediate failure of that connection.
Because ULP security mechanisms rely
on this aspect of Reliable Connected behavior,
implementations SHOULD cryptographically authenticate connection endpoints.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:35460fd7-b8e5-4c95-901c-fbe827b61966"
 title="Handle (STag) Predictability">
<t>
Implementations should use unpredictable memory handles
for any operation requiring exposed memory regions.
Exposing a continuously registered memory region
allows a remote host to read or write to that region
even when an RPC involving that memory is not underway.
Therefore, implementations should avoid
the use of persistently registered memory.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:958d6c42-3fa3-4368-9ea9-2f43b8795bcb"
 title="Memory Protection">
<t>
Requesters should register memory regions for remote access
only when they are about to be the target of an RPC transaction
that involves an RDMA Read or Write.
</t>
<t>
Requesters should invalidate memory regions
as soon as related RPC operations are complete.
Invalidation and DMA unmapping of memory regions should complete
before the receiver checks message integrity,
and
before the RPC consumer can use or alter the contents of the exposed memory region.
</t>
<t>
An RPC transaction on a Requester can terminate
before a Reply arrives, for example,
if the RPC consumer is signaled, or a segmentation fault occurs.
When an RPC terminates abnormally, memory regions associated with that RPC
should be invalidated before the Requester reuses those regions for other purposes.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:71519a0b-0458-4ae8-912d-2f09a968ab09"
 title="Denial of Service">
<t>
A detailed discussion of denial-of-service exposures
that can result from the use of an RDMA transport
appears in Section 6.4 of
<xref target="RFC5042"/>.
</t>
<t>
A Responder is not obliged to pull unreasonably large Read chunks.
A Responder can use an RDMA2_ERROR response
to terminate RPCs with unreadable Read chunks.
If a Responder transmits more data than
a Requester is prepared to receive in a Write or Reply chunk,
the RDMA provider typically terminates the connection.
For further discussion, see
<xref target="section:b1d23e5c-31df-483f-adb7-25430b5de38d"/>.
Such repeated connection termination can deny service
to other users sharing the connection from the errant Requester.
</t>
<t>
An RPC-over-RDMA transport implementation is not responsible
for throttling the RPC request rate,
other than to keep the number of concurrent RPC transactions
at or under the number of credits granted per connection (see
<xref target="section:45c67eb8-8dc6-47c3-8555-14270f1514bF"/>).
A sender can trigger a self-denial of service
by exceeding the credit grant repeatedly.
</t>
<t>
When an RPC transaction terminates due to
a signal
or
premature exit of an application process,
a Requester should invalidate the RPC's Write and Reply chunks.
Invalidation prevents the subsequent arrival of the Responder's Reply
from altering the memory regions associated with those chunks
after the Requester has released that memory.
</t>
<t>
On the Requester,
a malfunctioning application
or
a malicious user
can create a situation where RPCs initiate and abort continuously,
resulting in Responder replies that terminate
the underlying RPC-over-RDMA connection repeatedly.
Such situations can deny service to other users
sharing the connection from that Requester.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:4b069dfd-7532-4b9b-a9c9-1f0e8ee0d2fC"
 title="RPC Message Security">
<t>
ONC RPC provides cryptographic security via the RPCSEC_GSS framework
<xref target="RFC7861"/>.
RPCSEC_GSS implements
message authentication (rpc_gss_svc_none),
per-message integrity checking (rpc_gss_svc_integrity),
and
per-message confidentiality (rpc_gss_svc_privacy)
in a layer above the RPC-over-RDMA transport.
The integrity and privacy services require
significant computation and movement of data
on each endpoint host.
Some performance benefits enabled by RDMA transports can be lost.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:ca56ff24-b218-455a-9faf-c8f7c17bf26c"
 title="RPC-over-RDMA Protection at Other Layers">
<t>
For any RPC transport,
utilizing RPCSEC_GSS integrity or privacy services
has performance implications.
Protection below the RPC implementation is often
a better choice in performance-sensitive deployments,
especially if it, too, can be offloaded.
Certain implementations of IPsec can be co-located in RDMA hardware,
for example,
without change to RDMA consumers
and
with little loss of data movement efficiency.
Such arrangements can also provide a higher degree of privacy
by hiding endpoint identity
or
altering the frequency at which messages are exchanged,
at a performance cost.
</t>
<t>
Implementations MAY negotiate the use of protection
in another layer through the use of
an RPCSEC_GSS security flavor defined in
<xref target="RFC7861"/>
in conjunction with
the Channel Binding mechanism
<xref target="RFC5056"/>
and
IPsec Channel Connection Latching
<xref target="RFC5660"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:61deca2d-94c4-4fd4-be7a-59ae3a77c9a2"
 title="RPCSEC_GSS on RPC-over-RDMA Transports">
<t>
Not all RDMA devices and fabrics support the above protection mechanisms.
Also, NFS clients, where multiple users can access NFS files,
still require per-message authentication.
In these cases, RPCSEC_GSS can protect NFS traffic conveyed on RPC-over-RDMA connections.
</t>
<t>
RPCSEC_GSS extends the ONC RPC protocol without changing the format of RPC messages.
By observing the conventions described in this section,
an RPC-over-RDMA transport can convey RPCSEC_GSS-protected RPC messages interoperably.
</t>
<t>
Senders MUST NOT reduce protocol elements of RPCSEC_GSS
that appear in the Payload stream of an RPC-over-RDMA message.
Such elements include control messages
exchanged as part of establishing or destroying a security context,
or data items that are part of RPCSEC_GSS authentication material.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:17014ff8-d5ef-4db8-bbb5-337a07cd66e2"
 title="RPCSEC_GSS Context Negotiation">
<t>
Some NFS client implementations use a separate connection
to establish a Generic Security Service (GSS) context for NFS operation.
Such clients use TCP and the standard NFS port (2049) for context establishment.
Therefore, an NFS server MUST also provide
a TCP-based NFS service on port 2049 to enable the use of RPCSEC_GSS with NFS/RDMA.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:77AA4781-E811-4B0D-8704-F96CCD4888DF"
 title="RPC-over-RDMA with RPCSEC_GSS Authentication">
<t>
The RPCSEC_GSS authentication service has no impact
on the DDP-eligibility of data items in a ULP.
</t>
<t>
However, RPCSEC_GSS authentication material
appearing in an RPC message header can be larger than, say,
an AUTH_SYS authenticator.
In particular, when an RPCSEC_GSS pseudoflavor is in use,
a Requester needs to accommodate a larger RPC credential
when marshaling RPC Calls
and
needs to provide for a maximum size RPCSEC_GSS verifier
when allocating reply buffers and Reply chunks.
</t>
<t>
RPC messages, and thus Payload streams,
are larger on average as a result.
ULP operations that fit in a Simple Format message
when a simpler form of authentication is in use
might need to be reduced or conveyed via a Special Format message
when RPCSEC_GSS authentication is in use.
It is therefore more likely that a Requester provides
both a Read list and a Reply chunk
in the same RPC-over-RDMA Transport header
to convey a Special Format Call
and provision a receptacle for a Special Format Reply.
</t>
<t>
In addition to this cost,
the XDR encoding and decoding of each RPC message
using RPCSEC_GSS authentication
requires per-message host compute resources
to construct the GSS verifier.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:4574ad52-fe73-4679-a808-ae3612c60f24"
 title="RPC-over-RDMA with RPCSEC_GSS Integrity or Privacy">
<t>
The RPCSEC_GSS integrity service enables endpoints
to detect the modification of RPC messages in flight.
The RPCSEC_GSS privacy service prevents
all but the intended recipient
from viewing the cleartext content of RPC arguments and results.
RPCSEC_GSS integrity and privacy services are end-to-end.
They protect RPC arguments and results from application to server endpoint, and back.
</t>
<t>
The RPCSEC_GSS integrity and encryption services operate
on whole RPC messages after they have been XDR encoded,
and before they have been XDR decoded after receipt.
Connection endpoints use intermediate buffers
to prevent exposure of encrypted
or
unverified cleartext data to RPC consumers.
After a sender has
verified,
encrypted,
and
wrapped a message,
the transport layer MAY use RDMA data transfer
between these intermediate buffers.
</t>
<t>
The process of reducing a DDP-eligible data item removes
the data item
and
its XDR padding
from an encoded Payload stream.
In a non-protected RPC-over-RDMA message,
a reduced data item does not include XDR padding.
After reduction, the Payload stream contains fewer octets
than the whole XDR stream did beforehand.
XDR padding octets are often zero bytes, but they don't have to be.
Thus, reducing DDP-eligible items affects
the result of message integrity verification and encryption.
</t>
<t>
Therefore, a sender MUST NOT reduce a Payload stream
when RPCSEC_GSS integrity or encryption services are in use.
Effectively, no data item is DDP-eligible in this situation.
Senders can use only Simple and Continued Formats without chunks,
or Special Format.
In this mode, an RPC-over-RDMA transport operates
in the same manner as a transport that does not support DDP.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:0cddd345-064a-4c96-b251-17afce70219f"
 title="Protecting RPC-over-RDMA Transport Headers">
<t>
Like the header fields in an RPC message
(e.g., the xid and mtype fields),
RPCSEC_GSS does not protect the RPC-over-RDMA Transport stream.
XIDs, connection credit limits, and chunk lists
(though not the content of the data items they refer to)
are exposed to malicious behavior,
which can redirect data that is transferred by the RPC-over-RDMA message,
result in spurious retransmits,
or
trigger connection loss.
</t>
<t>
In particular,
if an attacker alters the information
contained in the chunk lists of an RPC-over-RDMA Transport header,
data contained in those chunks can be redirected
to other registered memory regions on Requesters.
An attacker might alter the arguments
of RDMA Read and RDMA Write operations on the wire
to gain a similar effect.
If such alterations occur,
the use of RPCSEC_GSS integrity or privacy services
enables a Requester to detect unexpected material in a received RPC message.
</t>
<t>
Encryption at other layers, as described in
<xref target="section:ca56ff24-b218-455a-9faf-c8f7c17bf26c"/>,
protects the content of the Transport stream.
RDMA transport implementations should conform to
<xref target="RFC5042"/>
to address attacks on RDMA protocols themselves.
</t>
</section>

</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:3b0e673b-98d7-436d-bd6f-180180503df6"
 title="Transport Properties">
<t>
Like other fields that appear in the Transport stream,
transport properties are sent in the clear with no integrity protection,
making them vulnerable to man-in-the-middle attacks.
</t>
<t>
For example, if a man-in-the-middle were to change the value
of the Receive buffer size, it could
reduce connection performance
or
trigger loss of connection.
Repeated connection loss can impact performance
or
even prevent a new connection from being established.
The recourse is to
deploy on a private network
or
use transport layer encryption.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:c85be87e-4f2b-4caf-8ae5-acdaa972a9f9"
 title="Host Authentication">
<t>
[ cel: This subsection is unfinished. ]
</t>
<t>
Wherein we use the relevant sections of
<xref target="RFC3552"/>
to analyze the addition of host authentication
to this RPC-over-RDMA transport.
</t>
<t>
The authors refer readers to Appendix C of
<xref target="RFC8446"/>
for information on how to design and test
a secure authentication handshake implementation.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:d235c884-6463-411f-ba34-6bcc82ab7a9f"
 title="IANA Considerations">
<t>
The RPC-over-RDMA family of transports have been assigned RPC netids
by
<xref target="RFC8166"/>.
A netid is an rpcbind
<xref target="RFC1833"/>
string used to identify the underlying protocol
in order for RPC to select appropriate transport framing
and the format of the service addresses and ports.
</t>
<t>The following netid registry strings are already defined for this purpose:
<figure align="left">
<artwork xml:space="preserve" align="left">
   NC_RDMA "rdma"
   NC_RDMA6 "rdma6"
</artwork>
</figure>
</t>
<t>
The "rdma" netid is to be used when IPv4 addressing is employed by the underlying transport,
and "rdma6" when IPv6 addressing is employed.
The netid assignment policy and registry are defined in
<xref target="RFC5665"/>.
The current document does not alter these netid assignments.
</t>
<t>
These netids MAY be used for any RDMA network that satisfies the
requirements of
<xref target="section:6903045e-bd1c-4e12-bf96-6b534989f46A"/>
and that is able to identify service endpoints using IP port addressing,
possibly through use of a translation service as described in
<xref target="section:e914de0a-05f3-4e14-a067-fb49a4f9b0ad"/>.
</t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>

<references
 title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.1833.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.4506.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5042.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5056.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5531.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5660.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5665.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7861.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7942.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8166.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8267.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8446.xml"?>
</references>

<references
 title="Informative References">

<?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-nfsv4-rpc-tls"?>

<reference
 anchor="IBA">
<front>
<title>InfiniBand Architecture Specification Volume 1</title>
<author>
<organization>InfiniBand Trade Association</organization>
</author>
<date month="March" year="2015"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Release" value="1.3"/>
<annotation>
Available from https://www.infinibandta.org/
</annotation>
</reference>

<reference
 anchor="CBFC">
<front>
<title>
Credit-Based Flow Control for ATM Networks: Credit Update Protocol, Adaptive Credit Allocation, and Statistical Multiplexing
</title>
<author initials="H.T." surname="Kung">
<organization>Division of Applied Sciences, Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>29 Oxford Street</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02138</code>
<country>United States of America</country>
</postal>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="T." surname="Blackwell">
<organization>Division of Applied Sciences, Harvard University</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>29 Oxford Street</street>
<city>Cambridge</city>
<region>MA</region>
<code>02138</code>
<country>United States of America</country>
</postal>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="A." surname="Chapman">
<organization>Bell-Northern Research</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street>P.O.Box 3511, Station C</street>
<city>Ottawa</city>
<region>Ontario</region>
<code>KIY 4H7</code>
<country>Canada</country>
</postal>
</address>
</author>
<date month="August" year="1994"/>
</front>
<seriesInfo name="Proc." value="ACM SIGCOMM '94 Symposium on Communications Architectures, Protocols and Applications, pp. 101-114."/>
</reference>

<?rfc include="reference.RFC.0768.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.0793.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.1094.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.1813.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.3552.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5040.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5041.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5532.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5661.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.5662.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.7530.xml"?>
<?rfc include="reference.RFC.8167.xml"?>
</references>

<section
 anchor="section:9e003b83-66b5-43d7-b9ef-0f271c8d301b"
 title="ULB Specifications">
<t>
Typically, an Upper-Layer Protocol (ULP) is defined
without regard to a particular RPC transport.
An Upper-Layer Binding (ULB) specification
provides guidance that helps a ULP interoperate
correctly and efficiently over a particular transport.
For RPC-over-RDMA version 2, a ULB may provide:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
A taxonomy of XDR data items that are eligible for DDP
</t>
<t>
Constraints on which upper-layer procedures
a sender may reduce,
and
on how many chunks may appear in a single RPC message
</t>
<t>
A method enabling a Requester to determine
the maximum size of the reply Payload
stream for all procedures in the ULP
</t>
<t>
An rpcbind port assignment for the RPC Program and Version
when operating on the particular transport
</t>
</list>
Each RPC Program and Version tuple that operates
on RPC-over-RDMA version 2 needs to have a ULB specification.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:2f2b32a4-d78a-45f0-b6a3-fa0e2d34a97b"
 title="DDP-Eligibility">
<t>
A ULB designates specific XDR data items as eligible for DDP.
As a sender constructs an RPC-over-RDMA message,
it can remove DDP-eligible data items from the Payload stream
so that the RDMA provider can place them
directly in the receiver's memory.
An XDR data item should be considered for DDP-eligibility
if there is a clear benefit to moving the contents
of the item directly from the sender's memory
to the receiver's memory.
</t>
<t>
Criteria for DDP-eligibility include:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The XDR data item is frequently sent or received, and its size is
often much larger than typical inline thresholds.
</t>
<t>
If the XDR data item is a result, its maximum size must be
predictable in advance by the Requester.
</t>
<t>
Transport-level processing of the XDR data item is not needed.
For example, the data item is an opaque byte array, which requires
no XDR encoding and decoding of its content.
</t>
<t>
The content of the XDR data item is sensitive to address alignment.
For example, a data copy operation would be required
on the receiver to enable the message to be parsed correctly,
or
to enable the data item to be accessed.
</t>
<t>
The XDR data item itself does not contain DDP-eligible data items.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
In addition to defining the set of data items that are DDP-eligible,
a ULB may limit the use of chunks
to particular upper-layer procedures.
If more than one data item in a procedure is DDP-eligible,
the ULB may limit the number of chunks
that a Requester can provide for a particular upper-layer procedure.
</t>
<t>
Senders never reduce data items that are not DDP-eligible.
Such data items can, however, be part of a Special Format payload.
</t>
<t>
The programming interface by which an upper-layer implementation
indicates the DDP-eligibility of a data item to the RPC transport
is not described by this specification.
The only requirements are
that the receiver can re-assemble
the transmitted RPC-over-RDMA message into a valid XDR stream
and
that DDP-eligibility rules specified by the ULB are respected.
</t>
<t>
There is no provision to express DDP-eligibility within the XDR
language.
The only definitive specification of DDP-eligibility is a ULB.
</t>
<t>
In general, a DDP-eligibility violation occurs when:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
A Requester reduces a non-DDP-eligible argument data item.
The Responder reports the violation as described in
<xref target="section:b1d23e5c-31df-483f-adb7-25430b5de38d"/>.
</t>
<t>
A Responder reduces a non-DDP-eligible result data item.
The Requester terminates the pending RPC transaction
and reports an appropriate permanent error to the RPC consumer.
</t>
<t>
A Responder does not reduce a DDP-eligible result data item into
an available Write chunk.
The Requester terminates the pending RPC transaction
and reports an appropriate permanent error to the RPC consumer.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:a3f15fe3-2677-4d94-adb5-afa80c7e197a"
 title="Maximum Reply Size">
<t>
When expecting small and moderately-sized Replies,
a Requester should rely on Message Continuation
rather than provision a Reply chunk.
For each ULP procedure where there is no clear Reply size maximum
and the maximum can be substantial,
the ULB should specify a dependable means
for determining the maximum Reply size.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:a5e8ada2-5473-4321-beee-41c29e04227f"
 title="Reverse-Direction Operation">
<t>
The direction of operation does not preclude
the need for DDP-eligibility statements.
</t>
<t>
Reverse-direction operation occurs
on an already-established connection.
Specification of RPC binding parameters is
usually not necessary in this case.
</t>
<t>
Other considerations may apply
when distinct RPC Programs
share an RPC-over-RDMA transport connection concurrently.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:e568723e-3dd8-4a54-9401-92ae4f98f88f"
 title="Additional Considerations">
<t>
There may be other details provided in a ULB.
<list style="symbols">
<t>
A ULB may recommend
inline threshold values
or
other transport-related parameters
for RPC-over-RDMA version 2 connections bearing that ULP.
</t>
<t>
A ULP may provide a means to communicate transport-related parameters
between peers.
</t>
<t>
Multiple ULPs may share
a single RPC-over-RDMA version 2 connection when
their ULBs allow the use of RPC-over-RDMA version 2
and
the rpcbind port assignments for those protocols permit connection sharing.
In this case, the same transport parameters (such as inline threshold)
apply to all ULPs using that connection.
</t>
</list>
Each ULB needs to be designed to allow correct interoperation
without regard to the transport parameters actually in use.
Furthermore, implementations of ULPs must be designed
to interoperate correctly
regardless of the connection parameters in effect on a connection.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:db58c83f-091c-481e-ba7c-a0246d1c475b"
 title="ULP Extensions">
<t>
An RPC Program and Version tuple may be extensible.
For instance,
the RPC version number may not reflect a ULP minor versioning scheme,
or
the ULP may allow the specification of additional features
after the publication of the original RPC Program specification.
ULBs are provided for interoperable RPC Programs and Versions by
extending existing ULBs to reflect the changes made necessary by each
addition to the existing XDR.
</t>
<t>
[ cel:
The final sentence is unclear, and may be inaccurate.
I believe I copied this section directly from RFC 8166.
Is there more to be said, now that we have some experience? ]
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:84e1ffc4-d916-4eb4-9fd8-a8218d084503"
 title="Extending RPC-over-RDMA Version 2">
<t>
This Appendix is not addressed to protocol implementers,
but rather to authors of documents that
extend the protocol specified in the current document.
</t>
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 extensibility facilitates
limited extensions to the base protocol
presented in the current document
so that new optional capabilities can be introduced
without a protocol version change
while maintaining robust interoperability
with existing RPC-over-RDMA version 2 implementations.
It allows extensions to be defined,
including the definition of new protocol elements,
without requiring modification or recompilation
of the XDR for the base protocol.
</t>
<t>
Standards Track documents may introduce extensions
to the base RPC-over-RDMA version 2 protocol in two ways:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
They may introduce new OPTIONAL transport header types.
<xref target="section:d4650151-40f0-4e85-8755-02c38cf8f444"/>
covers such transport header types.
</t>
<t>
They may define new OPTIONAL transport properties.
<xref target="section:a355adad-f03b-41a6-94a8-4128b10301bb"/>
describes such transport properties.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
These documents may also add the following sorts
of ancillary protocol elements to the protocol
to support the addition of
new transport properties and header types:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
They may create new error codes, as described in
<xref target="section:c2f5e937-d612-4e3a-a380-e0b15261f6a0"/>.
</t>
<t>
They may define new flags to use within the rdma_flags field,
as discussed in
<xref target="section:55a1749d-702c-48e4-b78c-0db392692c09"/>.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
New capabilities can be
proposed
and
developed
independently of each other.
Implementers can choose among them,
making it straightforward
to create
and
document
experimental features
and then bring them through the standards process.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:1c2304a3-0dc6-4ca1-b710-77a7b07f3d19"
 title="Documentation Requirements">
<t>
As described earlier,
a Standards Track document introduces a set of new protocol elements.
Together these elements are considered an OPTIONAL feature.
Each implementation is either
aware of all the protocol elements introduced by that feature
or
is aware of none of them.
</t>
<t>
Documents specifying extensions to RPC-over-RDMA version 2 should contain:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
An explanation of the purpose and use of each new protocol element.
</t>
<t>
An XDR description including all of the new protocol elements,
and a script to extract it.
</t>
<t>
A discussion of interactions with other extensions.
This discussion includes
requirements for other OPTIONAL features to be present,
or
that a particular level of support for an OPTIONAL facility is required.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Implementers combine the XDR descriptions
of the new features they intend to use
with
the XDR description of the base protocol in the current document.
This combination is necessary to create a valid XDR input file
because extensions are
free to use XDR types defined in the base protocol,
and
later extensions may use types defined by earlier extensions.
</t>
<t>
The XDR description for the RPC-over-RDMA version 2 base protocol
combined with that for any selected extensions
should provide a human-readable and compilable definition
of the extended protocol.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:d4650151-40f0-4e85-8755-02c38cf8f444"
 title="Adding New Header Types to RPC-over-RDMA Version 2">
<t>
New transport header types are defined similar to Sections
<xref
 format="counter"
 pageno="false"
 target="section:9af0d451-2ef3-454f-adb9-827664ccc39c"/>
through
<xref
 format="counter"
 pageno="false"
 target="section:07e8c178-62df-46a7-a57e-dcf107821d93"/>.
In particular, what is needed is:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
A description of the function and use of the new header type.
</t>
<t>
A complete XDR description of the new header type.
</t>
<t>
A description of how receivers report errors,
including mechanisms for reporting errors
outside the available choices already available
in the base protocol or other extensions.
</t>
<t>
An indication of whether a Payload stream must be present,
and a description of its contents
and
how receivers use such Payload streams to reconstruct RPC messages.
</t>
<t>
As appropriate, a statement of
whether a Responder may use Remote Invalidation
when sending messages that contain the new header type.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
There needs to be additional documentation that is made necessary
due to the OPTIONAL status of new transport header types:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The document should discuss constraints on support for the new header types.
For example, if support for one header type is implied or foreclosed
by another one, this needs to be documented.
</t>
<t>
The document should describe the preferred method
by which a sender determines whether its peer
supports a particular header type.
It is always possible to send a test invocation
of a particular header type to see if support is available.
However, when more efficient means are available
(e.g., the value of a transport property),
this should be noted.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:55a1749d-702c-48e4-b78c-0db392692c09"
 title="Adding New Header Flags to the Protocol">
<t>
New flag bits are to be defined similarly to Sections
<xref
 format="counter"
 pageno="false"
 target="section:4e23391c-b6a8-46b1-a399-c86f754b51bc"/>
and
<xref
 pageno="false"
 format="counter"
 target="section:fb299673-74f3-4f01-adb5-26a02ccd679f"/>.
Each new flag definition should include:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
An XDR description of the new flag.
</t>
<t>
A description of the function and use of the new flag.
</t>
<t>
An indication for which header types the flag value is meaningful,
and
for which header types it is an error to set the flag or to leave it unset.
</t>
<t>
A means to determine whether peers are prepared
to receive transport headers with the new flag set.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
There needs to be additional documentation that is made necessary
due to the OPTIONAL status of new flags:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The document should discuss constraints on support for the new flags.
For example, if support for one flag is implied or foreclosed
by another one, this needs to be documented.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:a355adad-f03b-41a6-94a8-4128b10301bb"
 title="Adding New Transport properties to the Protocol">
<t>
A Standards Track document defining a new transport property
should include the following information
paralleling that provided in this document
for the transport properties defined herein:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The rpcrdma2_propid value identifying the new property.
</t>
<t>
The XDR typedef specifying the structure of its property value.
</t>
<t>
A description of the new property.
</t>
<t>
An explanation of how the receiver can use this information.
</t>
<t>
The default value if a peer never receives the new property.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
There is no requirement that propid assignments
occur in a continuous range of values.
Implementations should not rely on all such values being small integers.
</t>
<t>
Before the defining Standards Track document is published,
the nfsv4 Working Group should select a unique propid value, and ensure that:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
rpcrdma2_propid values specified in the document do not conflict with
those currently assigned
or
in use by other pending working group documents defining transport properties.
</t>
<t>
rpcrdma2_propid values specified in the document do not conflict with
the range reserved for experimental use,
as defined in Section 8.2.
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
[ cel: There is no section 8.2. ]
<vspace blankLines="1"/>
[ cel: Should we request the creation of an IANA registry for propid values? ].
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
When a Standards Track document proposes additional transport properties,
reviewers should deal with possible security issues
exposed by those new transport properties.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:c2f5e937-d612-4e3a-a380-e0b15261f6a0"
 title="Adding New Error Codes to the Protocol">
<t>
The same Standards Track document that defines a new header type
may introduce new error codes used to support it.
A Standards Track document may similarly define
new error codes that an existing header type can return.
</t>
<t>
For error codes that do not require
the return of additional information,
a peer can use the existing RDMA_ERR2 header type to report the new error.
The sender sets the new error code
as the value of rdma_err with the result
that the default switch arm of the rpcrdma2_error (i.e., void) is selected.
</t>
<t>
For error codes that do require
the return of related information together with the error,
a new header type should be defined that returns the error
together with the related information.
The sender of a new header type needs to be prepared
to accept header types necessary to report associated errors.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:c2574344-5aec-427d-a5ed-048d7fcc0d95"
 title="Differences from RPC-over-RDMA Version 1">
<t>
The goal of RPC-over-RDMA version 2 is
to relieve certain constraints that have
become evident in RPC-over-RDMA version 1
with deployment experience:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA version 1 has been challenging to update
to address shortcomings or improve data transfer efficiency.
</t>
<t>
The average size of NFSv4 COMPOUNDs is significantly greater than
NFSv3 requests, requiring the use of Long messages for frequent operations.
</t>
<t>
Reply size estimation is awkward more often than expected.
</t>
</list>
This section details specific changes in RPC-over-RDMA version 2 that address these constraints directly.
</t>

<section
 anchor="section:d945b9f0-0666-4db7-9126-be57cf7b5f4f"
 title="Changes to the XDR Definition">
<t>
Several XDR structural changes enable
within-version protocol extensibility.
</t>
<t>
<xref target="RFC8166"/>
defines the RPC-over-RDMA version 1 transport header
as a single XDR object,
with an RPC message potentially following it.
In RPC-over-RDMA version 2,
there are separate XDR definitions of the transport header prefix (see
<xref target="section:2d1735f0-c465-43c6-9c18-3da6b7979862"/>),
which specifies the transport header type to be used,
and the transport header itself
(defined within one of the subsections of
<xref target="section:8039c7b8-9068-401e-9cbd-5c1e67d403e7"/>).
This construction is similar to an RPC message,
which consists of an RPC header (defined in
<xref target="RFC5531"/>)
followed by a message defined by an Upper-Layer Protocol.
</t>
<t>
As a new version of the RPC-over-RDMA transport protocol,
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 exists within the versioning rules defined in
<xref target="RFC8166"/>.
In particular, it maintains the first four words of the protocol header,
as specified in Section 4.2 of
<xref target="RFC8166"/>,
even though, as explained in
<xref target="section:e21d4f74-b536-47f2-9d07-c03a27a20de4"/>
of the current document,
the XDR definition of those words is structured differently.
</t>
<t>
Although each of the first four fields retains its semantic function,
there are differences in interpretation:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
The first word of the header, the rdma_xid field,
retains the format and function that it had in RPC-over-RDMA version 1.
Because RPC-over-RDMA version 2 messages can convey non-RPC messages,
a receiver should not use the contents of this field
without consideration of the protocol version and header type.
</t>
<t>
The second word of the header, the rdma_vers field,
retains the format and function that it had in RPC-over-RDMA version 1.
To clearly distinguish version 1 and version 2 messages,
senders need to fill in the correct version
(fixed after version negotiation).
Receivers should check that the content of the rdma_vers is correct
before using the content of any other header field.
</t>
<t>
The third word of the header, the rdma_credit field,
retains the size and general purpose that it had in RPC-over-RDMA version 1.
However, RPC-over-RDMA version 2 divides this field
into two 16-bit subfields. See
<xref target="section:45c67eb8-8dc6-47c3-8555-14270f1514bF"/>
for further details.
</t>
<t>
The fourth word of the header,
previously the union discriminator field rdma_proc,
retains its format and general function
even though the set of valid values has changed.
Within RPC-over-RDMA version 2,
this word is the rdma_htype field of the structure rdma_start.
The value of this field is now an unsigned 32-bit integer
rather than an enum type, to facilitate header type extension.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
Beyond conforming to the restrictions specified in
<xref target="RFC8166"/>,
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 tightly limits
the scope of the changes made to ensure interoperability.
Version 2 retains all existing transport header types used in version 1,
as defined in
<xref target="RFC8166"/>.
And, it expresses chunks in the same format and uses them the same way.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:630314a8-1cf5-40f7-a5ad-5bc12c719233"
 title="Transport Properties">
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 provides a mechanism
for exchanging an implementation's operational properties.
The purpose of this exchange is to help endpoints
improve the efficiency of data transfer
by exploiting the characteristics of both peers
rather than falling back on
the lowest common denominator default settings.
A full discussion of transport properties appears in
<xref target="section:86248e99-ca60-478a-8aff-3fb387410077"/>.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:5a2e5ff8-0f0b-454d-b9b3-c6773cd77780"
 title="Credit Management Changes">
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA transports employ credit-based flow control
to ensure that a Requester does not emit more RDMA Sends
than the Responder is prepared to receive.
</t>
<t>
Section 3.3.1 of
<xref target="RFC8166"/>
explains the operation of RPC-over-RDMA version 1 credit management
in detail.
In that design, each RDMA Send from a Requester
contains an RPC Call with a credit request,
and each RDMA Send from a Responder contains an RPC Reply
with a credit grant.
The credit grant implies that enough Receives
have been posted on the Responder to handle the credit grant
minus the number of pending RPC transactions
(the number of remaining Receive buffers might be zero).
</t>
<t>
Each RPC Reply acts as an implicit ACK
for a previous RPC Call from the Requester.
Without an RPC Reply message,
the Requester has no way to know that
the Responder is ready for subsequent RPC Calls.
</t>
<t>
Because version 1 embeds credit management in each message,
there is a strict one-to-one ratio between RDMA Send and RPC message.
There are interesting use cases that might be enabled
if this relationship were more flexible:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA operations that do not carry an RPC message,
e.g., control plane operations.
</t>
<t>
A single RDMA Send that conveys more than one RPC message,
e.g., for interrupt mitigation.
</t>
<t>
An RPC message that requires several sequential RDMA Sends,
e.g., to reduce the use of explicit RDMA operations for moderate-sized RPC messages.
</t>
<t>
An RPC transaction that requires multiple exchanges
or
an odd number of RPC-over-RDMA operations to complete.
</t>
</list>
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 provides
a more sophisticated credit accounting mechanism
to address these shortcomings.
<xref target="section:45c67eb8-8dc6-47c3-8555-14270f1514bF"/>
explains the new mechanism in detail.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:f7fb5108-58ea-4718-84be-5119a302f5f5"
 title="Inline Threshold Changes">
<t>
An "inline threshold" value is the largest message size (in octets)
that can be conveyed on an RDMA connection
using only RDMA Send and Receive.
Each connection has two inline threshold values:
one for messages flowing from client-to-server
(referred to as the "client-to-server inline threshold")
and one for messages flowing from server-to-client
(referred to as the "server-to-client inline threshold").
</t>
<t>
A connection's inline thresholds determine,
among other things,
when RDMA Read or Write operations are required
because an RPC message cannot be conveyed via a single RDMA Send and Receive pair.
When an RPC message does not contain DDP-eligible data items,
a Requester can prepare a Special Format Call or Reply
to convey the whole RPC message using RDMA Read or Write operations.
</t>
<t>
RDMA Read and Write operations require that data payloads
reside in memory registered with the local RNIC.
When an RPC completes,
that memory is invalidated to fence it from the Responder.
Memory registration and invalidation typically have a latency cost
that is insignificant compared to data handling costs.
</t>
<t>
When a data payload is small, however,
the cost of registering and invalidating
memory where the payload resides
becomes a significant part of total RPC latency.
Therefore the most efficient operation of an RPC-over-RDMA transport
occurs when the peers use explicit RDMA Read and Write operations
for large payloads but avoid those operations for small payloads.
</t>
<t>
When the authors of
<xref target="RFC8166"/>
first conceived RPC-over-RDMA version 1,
the average size of RPC messages
that did not involve a significant data payload
was under 500 bytes.
A 1024-byte inline threshold adequately minimized
the frequency of inefficient Long messages.
</t>
<t>
With NFS version 4
<xref target="RFC7530"/>,
the increased size of NFS COMPOUND operations
resulted in RPC messages that are, on average,
larger than previous versions of NFS.
With a 1024-byte inline threshold,
frequent operations such as GETATTR and LOOKUP
require RDMA Read or Write operations,
reducing the efficiency of data transport.
</t>
<t>
To reduce the frequency of Special Format messages,
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 increases the default size of inline thresholds.
This change also increases the maximum size
of reverse-direction RPC messages.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:1f3a1439-702f-4309-8733-5fa0e20555f4"
 title="Message Continuation Changes">
<t>
In addition to a larger default inline threshold,
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 introduces Message Continuation.
Message Continuation is a mechanism
that enables the transmission of a data payload
using more than one RDMA Send.
The purpose of Message Continuation is
to provide relief in several essential cases:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
If a Requester finds that it is inefficient
to convey a moderately-sized data payload using Read chunks,
the Requester can use Message Continuation to send the RPC Call.
</t>
<t>
If a Requester has provided insufficient Reply chunk space
for a Responder to send an RPC Reply,
the Responder can use Message Continuation to send the RPC Reply.
</t>
<t>
If a sender has to convey a sizeable non-RPC data payload
(e.g., a large transport property),
the sender can use Message Continuation to avoid having to register memory.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:16f03208-32cb-451d-90ab-a6f5f4b9e9b0"
 title="Host Authentication Changes">
<t>
For the general operation of NFS on open networks,
we eventually intend to rely on RPC-on-TLS
<xref target="I-D.ietf-nfsv4-rpc-tls"/>
to provide cryptographic authentication of the two ends of each connection.
In turn, this can improve the trustworthiness of AUTH_SYS-style user identities
that flow on TCP, which are not cryptographically protected.
We do not have a similar solution for RPC-over-RDMA, however.
</t>
<t>
Here, the RDMA transport layer already provides
a strong guarantee of message integrity.
On some network fabrics, IPsec or TLS
can protect the privacy of in-transit data.
However, this is not the case for all fabrics
(e.g., InfiniBand
<xref target="IBA"/>).
</t>
<t>
Thus, RPC-over-RDMA version 2 introduces a mechanism
for authenticating connection peers (see
<xref target="section:5f63e1b6-8d24-453b-b18b-b98ad66f3671"/>).
And like GSS channel binding,
there is also a way to determine when the use of host authentication is unnecessary.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:57c034d6-7129-4f7b-b8df-31e8bc691964"
 title="Support for Remote Invalidation">
<t>
When an RDMA consumer uses FRWR or Memory Windows to register memory,
that memory may be invalidated remotely [RFC5040].
These mechanisms are available when
a Requester's RNIC supports MEM_MGT_EXTENSIONS.
</t>
<t>
For this discussion, there are two classes of STags.
Dynamically-registered STags appear in a single RPC,
then are invalidated.
Persistently-registered STags survive longer than one RPC.
They may persist for the life of an RPC-over-RDMA connection
or even longer.
</t>
<t>
An RPC-over-RDMA Requester can provide
more than one STag in a transport header.
It may provide
a combination of dynamically- and persistently-registered STags in one RPC message,
or
any combination of these in a series of RPCs on the same connection.
Only dynamically-registered STags using Memory Windows or FRWR
may be invalidated remotely.
</t>
<t>
There is no transport-level mechanism
by which a Responder can determine
how a Requester-provided STag was registered,
nor whether it is eligible to be invalidated remotely.
A Requester that mixes persistently- and dynamically-registered STags in one RPC,
or mixes them across RPCs on the same connection,
must, therefore, indicate which STag the Responder may invalidate remotely
via a mechanism provided in the Upper-Layer Protocol.
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 provides such a mechanism.
</t>
<t>
A sender uses the RDMA Send With Invalidate operation
to invalidate an STag on the remote peer.
It is available only when both peers support MEM_MGT_EXTENSIONS
(can send and process an IETH).
</t>
<t>
Existing RPC-over-RDMA transport protocol specifications
<xref target="RFC8166"/>
<xref target="RFC8167"/>
do not forbid direct data placement in the reverse direction.
Moreover, there is currently no Upper-Layer Protocol
that makes data items in reverse direction operations
eligible for direct data placement.
</t>
<t>
When chunks are present in a reverse direction RPC request,
Remote Invalidation enables the Responder
to trigger invalidation of a Requester's STags
as part of sending an RPC Reply,
the same way as is done in the forward direction.
</t>
<t>
However, in the reverse direction, the server acts as the Requester,
and the client is the Responder.
The server's RNIC, therefore, must support receiving an IETH,
and the server must have registered its STags
with an appropriate registration mechanism.
</t>
</section>

<section
 anchor="section:e554df42-6e82-4e28-96a0-8f9872eb476c"
 title="Error Reporting Changes">
<t>
RPC-over-RDMA version 2 expands the repertoire of errors
that connection peers may report to each other.
The goals of this expansion are:
<list style="symbols">
<t>
To fill in details of peer recovery actions.
</t>
<t>
To enable retrying certain conditions
caused by mis-estimation of the maximum reply size.
</t>
<t>
To minimize the likelihood of a Requester waiting forever for a Reply
when there are communications problems that prevent the Responder
from sending it.
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section
 anchor="section:7b212a81-9c2a-4c05-891a-369cc7184585"
 title="Acknowledgments"
 numbered="no">
<t>
The authors gratefully acknowledge the work of Brent Callaghan
and Tom Talpey on the original RPC-over-RDMA version 1 specification
(RFC 5666).
The authors also wish to thank
Bill Baker, Greg Marsden, and Matt Benjamin
for their support of this work.
</t>
<t>
The XDR extraction conventions were
first described by the authors of the NFS version 4.1
XDR specification
<xref target="RFC5662"/>.
Herbert van den Bergh suggested the replacement sed
script used in this document.
</t>
<t>
Special thanks go to
Transport Area Director Magnus Westerlund,
NFSV4 Working Group Chairs Spencer Shepler
and
Brian Pawlowski,
and
NFSV4 Working Group Secretary Thomas Haynes
for their support.
</t>
</section>

</back>

</rfc>
